<query>
<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1979</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Established September 1993, under the provisions of the Park Act.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/72</http_url>
<id_number>72</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_72.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us,ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>61.1975833300</latitude><location>Kluane: Yukon Territory (Canada) and Alaska (USA)&#xd;
&#xd;
Glacier Bay:  Alaska (USA)&#xd;
&#xd;
Tatshenshini:  Province of British Columbia (Canada)</location>
<longitude>-140.9919722000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;A unique area with high mountain peaks, foothills, glacial systems, lakes, streams, valleys and coastal landscapes. The Wrangell-St Elias region represents the most extensive array of glaciers and ice fields outside the polar region. These features and the high mountains of the Wrangell-St Elias, Chugach and Kluane ranges have resulted in the region becoming known as the 'Mountain Kingdom' of North America. Geologically the mountains are included in the Pacific mountain system and include the 130&amp;nbsp;km long Bagley ice field, the second-highest peak in the USA (Mount St Elias) and the largest piedmont glacier on the North American continent (Malaspina Glacier). Extensive lowlands are found only in the centre and along north-western fringes of the region. Elsewhere lowlands are sandwiched between mountains and sea or occur as narrow valleys and plateaux grading into upland and serrated peaks. Principal drainages include the Copper, Chitina, White, Alsek and Donjek rivers and tributaries. The Malaspina foreland coastal area comprises mainly long, straight piedmont glacial beaches cut through by numerous often sizeable glacial-melt drainage-ways.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The wide ranges of climatic zones and elevations in the region have resulted in a great variety of ecosystems representing three major biomes or broad vegetational subdivisions: the coastal coniferous biome; the northern coniferous biome; and the alpine tundra biome. The coastal coniferous biome includes coastal spruce-hemlock forests, tall shrub thickets and bogs and marshes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The northern coniferous biome includes closed tall spruce and deciduous forests, open, low mixed evergreen and deciduous forests, tall shrub thickets and low shrub thickets.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The alpine tundra biome includes moist sedge and grass alpine tundra and dry alpine tundra: moist sedge and grass alpine tundra at 900-1,500&amp;nbsp;m on gradual slopes, meadow-like tundra composed of sedges and grasses interspersed with low shrubs such as blueberry and Labrador tea; and dry alpine tundra, on steeper mountain slopes and exposed ridges from 900&amp;nbsp;m to the elevation of perpetual ice and snow comprising low, matted alpine plants dominated by mountain avens.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There is a great variety of fauna reflecting the habitat diversity. Carnivores include coyote, grey wolf, red fox, short-tailed weasel, mink, wolverine, river otter, lynx and the more easily visible brown bear and black bear. A rare bluish colour phase of the black bear, known locally as the glacier bear, is centred in the vicinity of Yakutat. Other mammals include pica and snowshoe hare, arctic ground squirrel, beaver Castor, muskrat and porcupine. Rodents include the hoary marmot. Moose and caribou range in lower elevations and mountain goat and Dally sheep occupy high mountainous areas. Bison were introduced in 1950 and again in 1962. Black-tailed deer may occur along coastal fringes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The avifauna includes spruce grouse, ruffed grouse, willow ptarmigan, rock ptarmigan, white-tailed ptarmigan, trumpeter swan and many song birds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;All five species of Alaskan Pacific salmon including red salmon, chum, silver salmon, pink salmon and king salmon spawn in park or preserve waters. Freshwater fish species include Dolly Virden, lake trout, steelhead, cutthroat trout, arctic grayling, turbot, round whitefish and humpback whitefish.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>ter</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates>1992, 1994</secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;These parks comprise an impressive complex of glaciers and high peaks on both sides of the border between Canada (Yukon Territory and British Columbia) and the United States (Alaska). The spectacular natural landscapes are home to many grizzly bears, caribou and Dall's sheep. The site contains the largest non-polar icefield in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Kluane / Wrangell-St. Elias / Glacier Bay / Tatshenshini-Alsek</site>
<states>United States of America,Canada</states>
<transboundary>1</transboundary>
<unique_number>78</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(ix)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1995</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/354</http_url>
<id_number>354</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_354.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us,ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>48.9960555600</latitude><location>Province of Alberta, Canada; State of Montana, USA</location>
<longitude>-113.9041667000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The park is situated in the extreme south-west of the Province of Alberta, along the eastern slopes of the Continental Divide and at the western margin of the Canadian Great Plains region; it includes prairie, lakes and mountains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Local relief is dominated by the 2,500&amp;nbsp;m peaks of the Border and Clark Ranges, which are generally less rugged than their Glacier National Park counterparts. The park is centred on a long, narrow 'glacier trough' lake.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The most immediately obvious feature of the park is the sudden transition from prairie to mountain landscape; a contrast which is emphasized by the virtual absence of intervening foothills.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The dominant landforms of the park are of glacial origin; typical of both mountain and continental glaciations. The mountain valleys and rock basins were shaped by glacial erosion, whereas the rolling grasslands are a result of glacial deposition.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The joint Waterton-Glacier properties contain a stratigraphic record spanning more than 1,250&amp;nbsp;million years of sedimentary and tectonic evolution.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Waterton-Glacier area is at the centre of what has been described as a major floristic discontinuity which occurs at about 50&amp;deg; N latitude and which divides the southern ranges of the Rocky Mountains from the more northerly ranges. The prevalence of a maritime climate results in many species occurring which are closely related to the flora of the far west.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Five large ecoregions are found within Waterton-Glacier National Parks; these are alpine tundra, subalpine forest, montane forest, aspen parkland and fescue grassland.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The alpine tundra ecoregion is found above 2,100&amp;nbsp;m on the west slope and 1,800&amp;nbsp;m on the east. Arctic-alpine tundra vegetation covers much of the terrain, typical species including drays tundra and dwarf alpine poppy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The subalpine forest ecoregion is the single-most vegetation cover in the park. A strong boreal element is typical of this ecoregion, characterized by such species as dwarf birch and fireweed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The montane ecoregion (Canadian zone) occurs at low to mid elevations, but is largely restricted to the dry foothills and major river valleys of the eastern slopes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The aspen parkland ecoregion serves as a transition belt between the prairie grasslands and the coniferous forest zone, with dominant tree species being trembling aspen and balsam poplar. Commonly known as 'bunchgrass prairie', the fescue grasslands ecoregion is typified by the festuca/danthonia grass association. The park is noted for an abundance of wildlife and a wide diversity of habitats. Investigations have listed 61 species of mammals, 241 species of bird, and 20 species of fish; reptiles and amphibians have not been extensively studied. Carnivores include grey wolf, coyote, cougar, American black bear and mink. There is also a self-sustaining population of more than 200 grizzly bear in the Waterton-Glacier complex. Other ungulates include mule deer, white-tailed deer, moose, bison, mountain goat and bighorn sheep, the last two being indigenous to the region. Rodents include beaver and muskrat.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Waterton is located on the margin of two major avian migratory routes; the Central and Pacific flyways overlap here, and the marsh and lake areas of the park are used extensively as staging areas. Both the bald eagle and peregrine falcon pass through the area.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Fish fauna includes lake whitefish, cut-throat trout, rainbow trout, lake trout, bull trout &lt;em&gt;Salvelinus&lt;/em&gt; and Arctic grayling.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>rev</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;In 1932 Waterton Lakes National Park (Alberta, Canada) was combined with the Glacier National Park (Montana, United States) to form the world's first International Peace Park. Situated on the border between the two countries and offering outstanding scenery, the park is exceptionally rich in plant and mammal species as well as prairie, forest, and alpine and glacial features.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Waterton Glacier International Peace Park</site>
<states>United States of America,Canada</states>
<transboundary>1</transboundary>
<unique_number>407</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1978</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/4</http_url>
<id_number>4</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_4.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>51.4666666700</latitude><location>Province of Newfoundland and Labrador</location>
<longitude>-55.6166666700</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;At the tip of the Great Northern Peninsula of the island of Newfoundland, the remains of an 11th-century Viking settlement are evidence of the first European presence in North America. The excavated remains of wood-framed peat-turf buildings are similar to those found in Norse Greenland and Iceland.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Recognized in 1960, excavated from 1961 to 1968 and then from 1973 to 1976, and protected by Parks Canada since1977, the Epaves Bay archaeological site, which is located near Anse aux Meadows, at the northern extremity of Newfoundland is of great importance in the history of the settlement of Rwarica. The earliest sign of human activity go back roughly 5,000 years and among the prehistoric and protohistoric populations which succeeded one another is a well-defined branch of Eskirms (Dorset Eskimos) which has been shown to have existed from about AD 400-700. A temporary settlement for fishermen, this coastal site, which is located on a coastline covered by peat bogs, would appear to have been abandoned for roughly a century. During the 9th century it was re-established by an archaic native population similar to that from which, during the historic era, the Beothuk 'Indians' descended.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Until about 1500, this population maintained a quasi-permanent settlement, many traces of which have been found in the bay and surrounding area. This occupation, whether seasonal or continuous, was not the only presence in the area. The exceptional significance of l'Anse aux Meadows arises precisely from a temporary Viking settlement comprising eight houses, one forge and four workshops. The excavations provided detailed information on the settlement, implements and lifestyle of the occupants. The large houses (the most spacious of which measured respectively 24&amp;nbsp;m by 4.5&amp;nbsp;m and 19&amp;nbsp;m by 14&amp;nbsp;m) are characterized by the building techniques used, which are similar to those in use in Norway during the same period: a structure covered with turf taken from the peat bog; a type of especially pointed roof; thick peat partitions on the sod floors; layout of the rooms, fireplaces and openings. The objects found include a number which fall clearly within the categories of Viking artefacts such as a stone oil lamp, a balance, a birch bark case for a ballast stone, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Near the forge, the low-shaft furnace (which is partially conserved) a deposit of slag was found. The fifty-odd forged iron objects (nails, rivets, buckles, etc.) that were found both in the dwellings and workshops comply with the normal typology of late Viking settlements along the Norwegian coastline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The excavation of L'Anse aux Meadows was conducted on a vulnerable site and followed by extensive laboratory study. It was possible, thanks to a palaeo-ecological study making use of seed and pollen fossils, to reconstruct the long-term landscape and surroundings of this human settlement. In spite of the astonishing appearances of its archaeological vestiges, L'Anse aux Meadows is an outstanding property of human heritage. It is a precious and, until now, unique milestone in the history of human migration and the discovery of the universe: it is the oldest settlement of European origin in America.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;At the tip of the Great Northern Peninsula of the island of Newfoundland, the remains of an 11th-century Viking settlement are evidence of the first European presence in North America. The excavated remains of wood-framed peat-turf buildings are similar to those found in Norse Greenland and Iceland.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>L’Anse aux Meadows National Historic Site</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>7</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1978</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Established as a national park reserve in 1972. Accepted as a World Heritage site in 1978.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/24</http_url>
<id_number>24</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_24.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>61.5472222200</latitude><location>Northwest Territories</location>
<longitude>-125.5894444000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Located in the south-west corner of Northwest Territories, along the course of the South Nahanni and Flat rivers, the park lies in a diverse mountainous area comprising mountain ranges, rolling hills, elevated plateaus, deep canyons and huge waterfalls, as well as a unique limestone cave system.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The dissected sandstone, shale and limestone mountains ranges in the east and central areas of the park sharply contrast the Ragged Range of harder igneous rocks in the park's western extremity. The park encompasses parts of the Hyland Plateau, Selwyn Mountains, Liard Plateau, Mackenzie Plain and Mackenzie Mountains and a major part of the Nahanni River, one of North America's finest wild rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;In the valley below the Ragged Range, tufa mounds known as the Rabbitkettle Hotspring, rise in a succession of terraces to a height of 30&amp;nbsp;m. Other features of the area include three major canyons; Virginia Falls; extensive karst terrain with a complex underground river system, caves, labyrinths, closed canyons and sinkholes; wind eroded sandstone landforms known as the Sand Blowouts; and large areas that have remained unglaciated for up to 300,000 years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park contains transitional and vegetation types of two major biomes: Nearctic boreal forest; and Nearctic alpine tundra. All stages of boreal forest occur, from recent burns to mature spruce forests, and with associated variations on wet, mesic and dry habitats. Densely growing white spruce and poplar dominate valley bottoms. At higher altitudes and on the northern slopes, black spruce is more prominent. An area of spruce-larch/lichen taiga with several orchid species is present near Virginia Falls. Alpine tundra characterized by sedges, lichens, grasses and shrubs occurs on the higher mountains of the Tlogotsho, Headless and Funeral ranges. Wild mint, golden rod, yellow monkey-flower and aster are among the many flowering plants that grow in abundance near mineral springs in the vicinity of Flat River. Almost 600 species of vascular plant and 325 species of bryophyte have been identified in Nahanni.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;40 species of mammal, including grey wolf, grizzly bear, black bear, woodland caribou, moose, white-tailed deer, mountain goat, Dall's sheep and beaver are present. A total of 170 species of bird in 29 families have been observed including peregrine falcon, golden eagle, trumpeter swan and bald eagle. Arctic grayling and Dolly Varden trout occur in the streams that flow into the Nahanni and Flat rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The original inhabitants of this area are ethnologically known as Goat or Mountain Indians and Kaska Indians, who were found living in the area when the Northwest and Hudson Bay fur trading companies established their trading posts along the Mackenzie River in the 1820s.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Located along the South Nahanni River, one of the most spectacular wild rivers in North America, this park contains deep canyons and huge waterfalls, as well as a unique limestone cave system. The park is also home to animals of the boreal forest, such as wolves, grizzly bears and caribou. Dall's sheep and mountain goats are found in the park's alpine environment.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Nahanni National Park</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>27</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1979</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/71</http_url>
<id_number>71</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_71.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>50.7677777800</latitude><location></location>
<longitude>-111.4922222000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Dinosaur Provincial Park - located at the heart of Alberta's badlands - contains some of the most important fossil discoveries ever made from the 'Age of Reptiles', in particular about 35 species of dinosaur, dating back some 75&amp;nbsp;million years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Dinosaur Provincial Park is located in the &lt;a href="http://www.cd.gov.ab.ca/preserving/parks/anhic/drymixedgrass.asp"&gt;Dry Mixedgrass Subregion&lt;/a&gt; of the Grassland Natural Region. This is the warmest and driest subregion in Alberta. Permanent streams are relatively rare, although the ones that do exist are deeply carved into the bedrock in some places. This as exposed Cretaceous shales and sandstones, creating extensive badlands, the largest in Canada. &lt;a name="grassland"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a name="badlands"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Great rivers that flowed here 75&amp;nbsp;million years ago left sand and mud deposits that make up the valley walls, hills and hoodoos of modern-day Dinosaur Provincial Park. About 15,000 years ago this area was flat and covered by an ice sheet some 600&amp;nbsp;m thick. During this ice age, glacial melt water carved steep-sided channels; ice crystals, wind and flowing water continued to shape the badlands. Today, water from prairie creeks and run-off continues to sculpt the landscape and expose bedrock.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;During the late Cretaceous period, 75&amp;nbsp;million years ago, the landscape was very different. The climate was subtropical, with lush forests covering a coastal plain. Rivers flowed east, across the plain into the Bearpaw warm inland sea. The low swampy country was home to a variety of animals, including dinosaurs. The conditions were also perfect for the preservation of their bones as fossils. Between 1979 and 1991, a total of 23,347 fossil specimens were collected, including 300 dinosaur skeletons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Geological strata of the Judith River formation have yielded many of the dinosaur remains for which the park is renowned. Some 35 species of over 34 genera of 12 families of dinosaurs have been found in the park, including specimens from every known group of dinosaurs from the Cretaceous period. The families &lt;em&gt;Hadrasauridae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ornithomimidae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tyrannosauridae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nodosauridae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pachycephalosauridae&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ceratopsidae&lt;/em&gt; are best represented. Other fossil remains include fish, turtles, marsupials and amphibians.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;About 6% of the park is occupied by significant and, for the most part, undisturbed riparian habitat shaped by the meandering channel of the Red Deer River and characterized by point bars, wide terraces, fans and cut banks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The river terraces support lush and diverse vegetation in various successional stages, ranging from pioneer willow stands to structurally complex plains, cottonwood forest, tall shrub thickets, ephemeral wetlands and dense sagebrush flats. Plains cottonwood riparian communities are among the most threatened habitats in semi-arid regions. The 'badlands' provide habitat for a number of ecologically specialized plant species and are characterized by open vegetation dominated by plants of the genus Artemisia and the family &lt;em&gt;Chenopodiaceae&lt;/em&gt;. Remnant and recently created grasslands occur on buttes and large pediments.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The mild winter microclimate, coupled with an abundant food supply, provides critical winter range for native ungulates such as pronghorn, mule deer and white-tailed deer. The relative richness and abundance of breeding avifauna is noteworthy. Over 150 species of bird have been recorded. The area supports a number of species locally threatened or at their biogeographic limits, including golden eagle, prairie falcon, ferruginous hawk, loggerhead shrike, merlin, sparrow and grasshopper sparrow. Plains spade-foot toad also occurs.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to its particularly beautiful scenery, Dinosaur Provincial Park &amp;ndash; located at the heart of the province of Alberta's badlands &amp;ndash; contains some of the most important fossil discoveries ever made from the 'Age of Reptiles', in particular about 35 species of dinosaur, dating back some 75 million years.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Dinosaur Provincial Park</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>75</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1981</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/157</http_url>
<id_number>157</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_157.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>52.0950000000</latitude><location>Province of British Columbia</location>
<longitude>-131.2202778000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The village of Ninstints (Nans Dins) is located on a small island off the west coast of the Queen Charlotte Islands (Haida Gwaii), and it bears a unique testimony to the vanished civilization of the Haida Indians, a tribe living essentially from hunting and fishing in the archipelago.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The San Christoval Mountains form the backbone of Gwaii Haanas, rising to 1,123&amp;nbsp;m at Mount de la Touche. The higher elevations of this range are dominated by mountain hemlock and alpine tundra vegetation zones. The lower elevations are mainly cedar, pine and western hemlock. The hemlock-Sitka spruce zone is on the islands of the eastern part of Gwaii Haanas, including the eastern fringe of Moresby Island. The distinct island flora and fauna have evolved over thousands of years. The species here often differ from those found on the mainland. Many common continental species are not found on the islands at all, or have evolved into unique subspecies such as the black bear and pine marten (both larger than mainland cousins), deer mouse, dusky shrew and short-tailed weasel.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;An estimated 1.5&amp;nbsp;million seabirds nest along some 4,700&amp;nbsp;km of shoreline on the islands from May to late August. Approximately half of these seabirds can be found in Gwaii Haanas. Many are burrow-nesters, such as the rhinoceros auklet, ancient murrelet, tufted puffin, horned puffin, Cassin's auklet, Leach's storm petrel and fork-tailed storm petrel. Because the islands are situated along the Pacific flyway, dozens of species of migrating birds stop here in spring and autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The seas around Gwaii Haanas teem with life. These waters are home to salmon, herring, halibut, rockfish, mussels, crab, starfish, sea urchin and octopus, along with numerous other species. Haida Gwaii is also on the spring migration route of the grey whales which spend their summers in feeding grounds in the Bering Sea. Killer whales (orcas), humpback and minke whales are also seen in the waters surrounding Gwaii Haanas, along with dolphins, porpoises and harbour seals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The first traces of human occupation date back almost 2,000 years; the village was not deserted until shortly after 1880, when about 25 Indians still took up winter quarters there before leaving for summer hunting and fishing expeditions near Queen Charlotte Islands. A series of unit dwellings, cedar longhouses, still exists, of which 10 are in good condition. However, it is above all the 32 totemic and mortuary columns on the edge of the dwelling zone which contribute to the world renown of the site. These wooden columns, sculpted with stylized anthropo-zoomorphic figures, have suffered considerable erosion at the hands of nature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;More of the village has been taken by nature, consumed by age and the elements, and returned to the forest. What remains is unique in the world, a 19th-century Haida village where the ruins of ten houses and 32 memorial or mortuary poles bespeak the power and artistry of a rich and flamboyant society.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Haida have always thrived on the wealth of both the sea and the forest. Shellfish and salmon were staple foods. Giant Western red cedars were the raw material of ocean-going canoes, vast post-and-plank houses, and great poles bearing both symbols of family history and holding inside them the bones of ancestors. The Haida lived on SGaang Gwaii for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Remains of houses, together with carved mortuary and memorial poles, illustrate the Haida people's art and way of life. The site commemorates the living culture of the Haida people and their relationship to the land and sea, and offers a visual key to their oral traditions. Gwaii Haanas is a protected area that contains the essence of the rugged beauty and ecological character of the Pacific coast. It is a celebration of more than 10,000 years of connection between land, sea and Haida culture.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The village of Ninstints (Nans Dins) is located on a small island off the west coast of the Queen Charlotte Islands (Haida Gwaii). Remains of houses, together with carved mortuary and memorial poles, illustrate the Haida people's art and way of life. The site commemorates the living culture of the Haida people and their relationship to the land and sea, and offers a visual key to their oral traditions.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>S&lt;U&gt;G&lt;/U&gt;ang Gwaay</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>175</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1981</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/158</http_url>
<id_number>158</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_158.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>49.7494444400</latitude><location>Province of Alberta</location>
<longitude>-113.6238889000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated in south-west Alberta, Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump is one of the most important hunting sites identified to date. At the edge of a landscape of hills and of highlands cut by natural passes, a high sandstone cliff falls off to the east. This coastal relief lends itself ideally to primitive hunting methods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years the native people of the plains hunted the North American bison. The plains Indian lifestyle became dependent on hunting buffalo, and they adapted numerous hunting techniques to obtain their livelihood. The most sophisticated technique developed by the native people to kill buffalo was the buffalo jump. Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump is one of the oldest and best preserved sites of this kind with its elaborate drive lane complex and deep archaeological deposits still intact.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The site was used for the slaughter of bison from 3600 BC to 2600 BC, then intermittently towards 900 BC, and finally, continuously from AD 200 to 1850. Explored for the first time in 1938, it has since 1960 been the object of systematic excavations which have considerably enriched the knowledge of prehistoric arms and tools, and above all, transformed current thinking on the use of game as food and in clothing and lodging.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;West of the cliff lies a large drainage basin 40&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in extent. This is a natural grazing area with plenty of water and mixed grass which remains fresh well into the fall. This natural grazing area attracted herds of buffalo late into the fall.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;To start the hunt, 'buffalo runners', young men trained in animal behaviour, would entice the herd to follow them by imitating the bleating of a lost calf. As the buffalo moved closer to the drive lanes (long lines of stone cairns were built to help the hunters direct the buffalo to the cliff kill site), the hunters would circle behind and upwind of the herd and scare the animals by shouting and waving robes. As the buffalo stampeded towards the edge of the cliff, the animals in front would try to stop but the sheer weight of the herd pressing from behind would force the buffalo over the cliff.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Below the cliff kill site are deep stratified deposits that contain evidence of use going back more than 5,700 years. These deposits consist of accumulated layers of dirt, stone rubble and bones referred to as loess. Over thousands of years of use, the loess has accumulated to a depth of over 11&amp;nbsp;m. Artefacts found in the kill site include bone, worn or broken stone tools and resharpening flakes, thousands of stone points, dart points and arrow heads. A few stone knives and choppers have also been found.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The flat area immediately below the kill site was where the hunters camped while they finished butchering the buffalo. A few tipi rings, the stones used to anchor tipis against the wind, can still be seen on the prairie level. It was here that meat was sliced into thin strips and hung on racks to dry in the sun. Large leg bones were smashed to remove the nutritious marrow, and the numerous boiling pits excavated by archaeologists in this area indicate these broken bones were also boiled to render grease. Boiling was done by throwing red-hot rocks into hide-lined pits filled with water.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump is associated with human survival during the prehistoric period and bears witness to a custom practised by the peoples of the North American plains for some 6,000 years. By its size, Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump broadly outdistances analogous sites discovered in the 19th century in Europe, such as Solutr&amp;eacute; in France (slaughter of wild horses) or Vestonice in Czechoslovakia (slaughter of young mammoths).&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;In south-west Alberta, the remains of marked trails and an aboriginal camp, and a tumulus where vast quantities of buffalo (American Bison) skeletons can still be found, are evidence of a custom practised by aboriginal peoples of the North American plains for nearly 6,000 years. Using their excellent knowledge of the topography and of buffalo behaviour, they killed their prey by chasing them over a precipice; the carcasses were later carved up in the camp below.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>176</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1983</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;1922 (as 2,600,OOOha), expanded in 1926. Includes much of the Whooping Crane Summer Range and the Peace-Athabaska Delta (Wood Buffalo National Park section), both designated as Ramsar sites ln May 1982.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/256</http_url>
<id_number>256</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_256.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>59.3583333300</latitude><location>Northwest Territories and Alberta</location>
<longitude>-112.2933333000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated on the Northern Boreal Plains in the north-central region of Canada, Wood Buffalo comprises a vast wilderness area (44,807&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ) which is home to North America's largest population of wild bison. It is also the natural nesting place of the whooping crane. Another of the park's attractions is the world's largest inland delta, located at the mouth of the Peace and Athabasca rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park has four main landscape featues: a glacially eroded plateau; glaciated plains; a major freshwater delta formed by three major rivers; and alluvial river lowlands. The lowlands and floodplains of Peace, Athabasca and Slave rivers and the delta in Lake Athabasca exhibit classic fluvial landforms, with a complex series of meander scars, oxbow lakes and former river terraces, and good examples of birds-foot delta development. During dry periods, the mudflats of one plain are dominated by mineral salts. These salt plains are unique in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetation is typical of the boreal forest zone with white spruce, black spruce, jack pine and tamarack predominant. Many watercourses have stands of balsam poplar and some upland has almost pure stands of aspen. Extensive stands of white spruce forests cover the banks of Peace, Athabasca and Birch rivers. The upper surface of the plateau is about 1,500&amp;nbsp;m above the rest of the park and supports a spruce-willow-birch upland tundra community. Some areas of prairie occur.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Shrublands of willow and alder occur where wet marsh soils meet drier forest soils. There is also extensive muskeg in the west and north of the park, an association of black spruce, sphagnum moss and northern heath plants.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park contains the largest undisturbed grass and sedge meadows in North America. The park was created specifically to protect North American bison, one of the largest free-roaming, self-regulating herds in existence, and consisting of a cross between 'wood' bison and 'plains' bison.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of a few sites where the predator-prey relationship between wolves and bison still exists. A total of 46 other mammal species have been recorded including black bear, woodland caribou, Arctic fox, moose, grey wolf, lynx, snowshoe hare, muskrat, beaver and mink. Occasionally animals more common to southern Canada are seen, such as red fox, porcupine and white-tailed deer. The caves of karstlands provide essential hibernation sites for bats.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;A total of 227 bird species have been recorded which include great grey owl and snowy owl, willow ptarmigan, redpoll crossbill and boreal chickadee. This is the only breeding site of whooping crane; peregrine falcon and bald eagle also breed within the park. The Peace-Athabasca Delta is an important area for migrant waterfowl including snow geese, white-fronted geese and Canada geese, whistling swan, diver, all seven species of North American grebe and species of duck.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Reptiles and amphibians are severely limited in numbers, but Canadian toad, leopard frog and red-sided garter snake reach their northern limits here. Boreal chorus frog and wood frog are also found in aquatic habitats. The fish fauna has been poorly studied, although there are a wide variety of aquatic habitats. 36 species have been recorded to date, four of them introduced.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated on the plains in the north-central region of Canada, the park (which covers 44,807 km2) is home to North America's largest population of wild bison. It is also the natural nesting place of the whooping crane. Another of the park's attractions is the world's largest inland delta, located at the mouth of the Peace and Athabasca rivers.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Wood Buffalo National Park</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>286</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iv)(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1985</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/300</http_url>
<id_number>300</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_300.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>46.8094444400</latitude><location>Province of Quebec, City of Quebec</location>
<longitude>-71.2105555600</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Qu&amp;eacute;bec illustrates one of the major stages in the population and growth of the Americas during the modern and contemporary period. When Samuel de Champlain founded Qu&amp;eacute;bec, the capital of New France, in 1608 he chose the natural site of a steep plateau overlooking the St Laurent River. The old heart of the city was established on this promontory, Cap-aux-Diamants, which is protected by Fort St Louis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Qu&amp;eacute;bec, which was a fortified city, a centre of population, and a harbour where ships delivered manufactured goods from Europe and loaded the precious pelts from the Great North, had an urban organization very early on and a zoning system which stemmed from these various functions. The cliff obviously divided the city into two districts: the district of business, barter, and the navy located in the Lower City, and the administrative and religious centre which gradually took hold in the Upper City.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Under English domination from 1759 to 1867 urban growth stayed within the limits of the site, and so the city expanded towards the west, all the way to the ramparts built in 1720 by Gaspard Chaussegros de L&amp;eacute;ry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The construction of a citadel at the far south-east end of Cap-aux-Diamants by the engineer Elias Durnford from 1819 to 1831 and the expansion of the system of fortifications to cover the city's entire perimeter were in keeping with the original spatial organization of the city and gave Qu&amp;eacute;bec its current topographical features. The city is an early example of urban heritage conservation as a result of the action of Lord Dufferin, who from 1875 to 1880 took a stand against the demolition of the fortifications which, from a strategic standpoint, had become useless. He simply had new gates to the city cut into them. From the beginning of the 20th century, and so well before being classified as a historic monument in 1957, the fortified walls of Qu&amp;eacute;bec were maintained by Canadian government funds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The oldest quarters are located in the Lower City in the vicinity of the Place Royale, which along with the Rue Notre Dame is lined with old 17th- and 18th-century houses. Notre-Dame des Victoires Church, which was built starting in 1688 according to Claude Baillif's plans and which was burned down during the siege of 1759, was rebuilt during the English domination. In the Upper City, the convents of the Jesuits (1625), the Recollet&amp;eacute;s (1629) and the Ursulines (1642), along with the Seminary (1663), have not retained their original form. However, despite the vicissitudes of history (the siege of 1759, great fires in the 18th and 19th centuries) they have retained some of the original elements. Of the 700 old civil or religious buildings remaining, 2% date back to the 17th century, 9% to the 18th century and 43% to the first half of the 19th century. At the same time, the city took on its present aspect, which was greatly influenced by the Baillairg&amp;eacute;s, a dynasty of architects who, for several generations, imposed an interesting interpretation of the neoclassical style.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;A coherent urban ensemble, Qu&amp;eacute;bec's historic district, including the citadel, the Upper City defended by walls with bastions, and the Lower City with its harbour and old quarters, provides an outstanding example of a fortified colonial town, which is by far the most complete in North America.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Qu&amp;eacute;bec was founded by the French explorer Champlain in the early 17th century. It is the only North American city to have preserved its ramparts, together with the numerous bastions, gates and defensive works which still surround Old Qu&amp;eacute;bec. The Upper Town, built on the cliff, has remained the religious and administrative centre, with its churches, convents and other monuments like the Dauphine Redoubt, the Citadel and Ch&amp;acirc;teau Frontenac. Together with the Lower Town and its ancient districts, it forms an urban ensemble which is one of the best examples of a fortified colonial city.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Historic District of Old Québec</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>336</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1984</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Jasper National Park &lt;br /&gt;Created a national park in 1930. First protected as Jasper Forest Park (1,295,000ha) in 1907. Accepted as a World Heritage Site (in combination with Kootenay, Banff and Yoho national parks) in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Yoho National Park &lt;br /&gt;1886. Accepted as a World Heritage site (in combination with Jasper, Kootenay and Banff national parks) in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Banff National Park &lt;br /&gt;1885 as a park reserve (2,600ha) around the Cave and Basin mineral hot springs. Formally established in 1887 as Rocky Mountains Park (67,300ha), Canada's first national park, under the Rocky Mountains Park Act. Named as Banff National Park (669,500ha) in 1930 under the National Parks Act. Deletion of S,400ha in 1949. Accepted as part of the World Heritage Site, Canadian Rockies, in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/304</http_url>
<id_number>304</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_304.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>51.4247222200</latitude><location>Provinces of British Columbia and Alberta</location>
<longitude>-116.4797222000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks comprises Banff National Park, Hamber Provincial Park, Jasper National Park, Kootenay National Park, Mount Robson Provincial Park, Mount Assiniboine Provincial Park and Yoho National Park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Rocky Mountains are oriented in a south-eastern to north-western direction along the Continental Divide and consist of the Western Ranges, the Main Ranges, the Front Ranges and the Foothills, all of which are represented within the parks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Active glaciers and ice fields still exist throughout the region, particularly in the Main Ranges. The most significant is the Columbia ice field, the largest in North America's subarctic interior. Covering 325&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; , the ice field spans the Continental Divide and the boundary between Jasper and Banff National Parks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Columbia ice fields of Jasper National Park are regarded as the hydrographic apex of North America and are the headwaters to three major river systems: the North Saskatchewan River, the Athabasca River and the Columbia River. The park waters of Yoho flow to the Pacific along Kicking Horse. Mount Robson Park encompasses the headwaters of Fraser River while Hamber Park encompasses Fortress Lake watershed. There are numerous lakes in Mount Assiniboine Park, most of which are located in broad alpine valleys and plateaus where they occupy glacially scoured depressions in the limestone bedrock.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Rockies have been divided into three life zones or ecoregions: montane, subalpine and alpine. Montane vegetation occurs in major valley bottoms, on the foothills and sun-exposed slopes of lower mountain sides, especially in the front ranges. Forest is generally found between 1,200&amp;nbsp;m and 1,800&amp;nbsp;m and typical species include Douglas fir, white spruce, aspen and poplar. Montane wetlands and meadows occupy areas adjacent to major rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The subalpine ecoregion occupies mountainsides between 1,800&amp;nbsp;m and 2,100&amp;nbsp;m, and valley bottoms of high elevations. This is the most extensive ecoregion in the Rockies and can be subdivided into lower and upper subalpine. The alpine ecoregion occurs above the timberline. It is characterized by diminutive and hardy vegetation such as low-growing willow and dwarf birch, heath, mountain avens and sedge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;A total of 56 mammalian species have been recorded. Characteristic species found in alpine meadows include Rocky Mountain goat, bighorn sheep, northern pika and hoary marmot. Forest mammals include moose, mule deer, white-tailed deer, caribou, red deer and red squirrel. Carnivores include grey wolf, grizzly bear, black bear, wolverine, lynx and puma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Some 280 avifaunal species have been noted, including northern three-toed woodpecker, white-tailed ptarmigan, grey jay, mountain bluebird, Clark's nutcracker, golden eagle, mountain chickadee and rock pipit. Other recorded fauna includes one species of toad, three species of frog, one species of salamander and two species of snake.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>Bis</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates>1990</secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The contiguous national parks of Banff, Jasper, Kootenay and Yoho, as well as the Mount Robson, Mount Assiniboine and Hamber provincial parks, studded with mountain peaks, glaciers, lakes, waterfalls, canyons and limestone caves, form a striking mountain landscape. The Burgess Shale fossil site, well known for its fossil remains of soft-bodied marine animals, is also found there.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>342</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1987</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Established under a Federal/Provincial Agreement signed by the Governments of Canada and Newfoundland and Labradc on 13 August 1973. The same authorities amended this agreement on 18 May 1983, whereby approximately 9,300ha were returned to the province. The park is currently being formally established under the National Parks Act (Parks Canada, 1986). Inscribed on the World Heritage List in 1987.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/419</http_url>
<id_number>419</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_419.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>49.6125000000</latitude><location>Provinces of Newfoundland and Labrador</location>
<longitude>-57.5313888900</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Located on the western shore of the Great Northern Peninsula of Newfoundland, the park provides a rare example of the process of continental drift, where deep ocean crust and the rocks of the Earth's mantle lie exposed. More recent glacial action has resulted in some spectacular scenery, with coastal lowland, alpine plateau, fjords, glacial valleys, sheer cliffs, waterfalls and many pristine lakes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park comprises part of the Long Range Mountains on the Gulf of St Lawrence. The park includes coastal lowlands and an alpine plateau. The marine areas included in the park covers the inner portion of St Paul's Inlet, intertidal zones and estuaries. The shoreline features beaches, steep cliffs, and dune formations up to 30&amp;nbsp;m in height.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;An upland alpine plateau with perched lakes, bare rock and valleys, covers a large proportion of the eastern central park. The serpentine hills in the south-west comprise ultra-basic igneous rocks, which, due to high heavy metal content, inhibit most plant life. A number of steep sided, glacial valleys cut through the Long Range scarp face, forming deep, oligotrophic fjords, with vertical cliffs up to 685&amp;nbsp;m high. A number of waterfalls are fed in the summer by snow-melt at higher altitudes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is geologically diverse with areas of Ordovician sedimentary rocks, Precambrian granite and gneiss, Palaeozoic serpentinized ultra-basic rocks, gabbros, volcanic and Lower Palaeozoic sedimentary rocks. Exposed oceanic crust, mantle, a section of ancient Mohorovicic discontinuity, and other distinctive geological features are also found. There is also an unusually complete palaeotological sequence which has been proposed as the world stratotype for the Cambrian-Ordovician boundary.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are up to 36 distinct vegetation types and communities, with some vascular species and bryophytes, representing about 60% of Newfoundland's insular flora.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The coast includes typical shoreline communities, active dunes with white spruce, and cliffs with prostrate spruce and balsam fir. The coastal plain further inland has a number of plant communities including a mosaic of sedges in meadows with American larch scrub. Black spruce dominates wet, oligotrophic sites and balsam fir is found in more protected and mesic areas. Tundra vegetation has developed on the plateau above this and varies from small areas of coniferous forest and stunted forest to bare rock.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Faunal diversity resembles an oceanic rather than continental-shelf island and is markedly reduced compared with the mainland. However a number of species scarce in Canada are found, including lynx, caribou and arctic hare. The more common marine mammals that can be observed from the park, albeit with a diminishing frequency in recent years include pilot, minke and finback whales and harbour seals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The avifauna comprises arctic, boreal and pelagic species, with strays from mainland, the north-west Atlantic and Europe. The park is a significant breeding site for harlequin duck, blackpoll warbler, common tern and arctic tern, a nesting site for bald eagle, rock ptarmigan and American tree sparrow, and a stopover for migrating shore birds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Anadromous Atlantic salmon and arctic char are found in park waters and also in permanent freshwater form in certain landlocked lakes on the Long Range Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of archaeological sites in the park and human habitation can be traced back to the Maritime Archaic Indians (4,500-3,000 years ago) and the Dorset Eskimos (1,800-1,200 years ago). Europeans settled the area from the late 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated on the west coast of the island of Newfoundland, the park provides a rare example of the process of continental drift, where deep ocean crust and the rocks of the earth's mantle lie exposed. More recent glacial action has resulted in some spectacular scenery, with coastal lowland, alpine plateau, fjords, glacial valleys, sheer cliffs, waterfalls and many pristine lakes.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Gros Morne National Park</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>483</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1999</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/686</http_url>
<id_number>686</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_686.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Criterion (viii):&lt;/em&gt; In its representation of vertebrate life, Miguasha is the most outstanding fossil site in the world for illustrating the Devonian as the &amp;ldquo;Age of Fishes&amp;rdquo;. The area is of paramount importance in having the greatest number and best preserved fossil specimens found anywhere in the world of the lobe-finned fishes that gave rise to the first four-legged, air-breathing terrestrial vertebrates - the tetrapodes.&lt;/p&gt;</justification>
<latitude>48.1050000000</latitude><location>Gaspé Peninsula, Province of Quebec</location>
<longitude>-66.3530555600</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The palaeontological site of Miguasha National Park, in south-eastern Quebec on the southern coast of the Gasp&amp;eacute; Peninsula, is considered to be the world's most outstanding illustration of the Devonian period known as the 'Age of Fishes'.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Dating from 370&amp;nbsp;million years ago, the Upper Devonian Escuminac Formation represented here contains six of the eight fossil fish groups associated with this period. Its significance stems from the discovery of the highest number and best-preserved fossil specimens of the lobe-finned fishes that gave rise to the first four-legged, air-breathing terrestrial vertebrates - the tetrapods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;This 1&amp;nbsp;km wide formation extends for a distance of 8&amp;nbsp;km along the north shore of the Ristigouche River. The formation, extending 300-600&amp;nbsp;m underground, is represented by four distinct outcrops. The most important of these extends for a distance of 3&amp;nbsp;km and basically constitutes the park. Constituted essentially of grey rock sediments, the Escuminac Formation (dating from 350-375&amp;nbsp;million years ago) is composed of alternating layers of thick sandstone, silt and calcareous schists. The Fleurant Formation is found at the base of the Formation, while the summit is lined by the carboniferous Bonaventure Formation, whose reddish colour is the origin of the word &lt;em&gt;Miguasha&lt;/em&gt; in the language of the Micmacs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The flora and fauna fossils of Miguasha are particularly important in representing ichthyological fauna (fishes) of the Devonian period. Of the eight groups attached to this period, also known as the 'Age of Fishes', six are found at Miguasha, the other two being typically marine; this representation is uncommon among sites of the same age throughout the world. The site is also distinguished by invertebrates, plants and spore fossils (over 70 spore species) which, along with geochemical studies, have allowed a picture of the Devonian ecosystem to be constructed. Furthermore, the site is characterized by the exceptional condition of fossil remains, allowing, for example, study of soft body parts represented in gill imprints, digestive traces and cartilaginous elements of skeleton. Of particular importance is the presence of the crossopterygian group, typified by &lt;em&gt;Eusthenopteron foordi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Elpistostege watsoni&lt;/em&gt;. Nicknamed the 'Prince of Miguasha', the &lt;em&gt;Eusthenopteron&lt;/em&gt;, which share many characteristics with the tetrapods, have largely resulted in the focused attention of the international scientific community on the Escuminac Formation. Indeed, it was the discovery and study of Eusthenopteron which notably gave rise to the modern conception of evolution from fish to terrestrial tetrapod vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Following taxa present an evolutive and phylogenetic interest: &lt;em&gt;Archaeopteris&lt;/em&gt; belongs to &lt;em&gt;Gymnosperma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spermasposita&lt;/em&gt; is considered as the oldest flowering plant, while &lt;em&gt;Petaloscorpio&lt;/em&gt; is the first terrestrial scorpion. The macroflora includes 10 species belonging to the first vascular plants of Devonian forests, and the microflora is composed of 80 spore species.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;For more than a century, the flora and fauna fossils of Miguasha have been recognized as unique, manifest by the large numbers of scientists and collectors from Europe and America who have visited the Escuminac Formation. The site is particularly important in representing ichthyological fauna (fishes) of the Devonian period.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>Rev</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The palaeontological site of Miguasha National Park, in south-eastern Quebec on the southern coast of the Gasp&amp;eacute; peninsula, is considered to be the world's most outstanding illustration of the Devonian Period known as the 'Age of Fishes'. Dating from 370 million years ago, the Upper Devonian Escuminac Formation represented here contains five of the six fossil fish groups associated with this period. Its significance stems from the discovery there of the highest number and best-preserved fossil specimens of the lobe-finned fishes that gave rise to the first four-legged, air-breathing terrestrial vertebrates &amp;ndash; the tetrapods.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Miguasha National Park</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>812</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iv)(v)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1995</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;The narrow peninsula on which Lunenburg was built was first settled formally in 1753, when German, Swiss, and Montbeliardian French immigrants were brought to Nova Scotia under a British colonization plan. A rigid gridiron plat was superimposed on the slope of the steep hill rising up from the harbour. The new settlement was named Lunenburg after the Royal house of Brunswick-L&amp;uuml;neberg, from which the Hanoverian Kings of England were descended. The 1453 largely German-speaking protestants who migrated to Lunenburg in 1752-53 represent the most northerly German settlement in North America in the 18th century. German customs and the German language survived an unusually long time in Lunenburg, owing to its relative isolation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Lunenburg was the second British colonial "model" town plan, after Halifax (1749). The model town was an important aspect of imperial policy for the British, to provide the functional space thought necessary for the smooth working of a colony. The model for laying out new towns in the colonies was created by the Board of Trade and Plantations. The Lunenburg plan (1753) incorporated all the principles Of the model town: geometrically regular streets and blocks; the allocation of public spaces; an allowance for fortifications; and a distinction between urban and non-urban areas. Of these all but the fortifications survive in present-day Lunenburg.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The town is home to the oldest continuous worshipping Lutheran and Presbyterian congregations in Canada, both having been founded in 1753.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;During the 19th century the town developed a strong economy based on fishing and shipbuilding. These industries expanded in the 20th century. In the 1850s it sent the first fleet to the Grand Banks; in the 1870S it revolutionized the industry with the introduction of "double dory" trawl fishing; in the 19205 it was at the forefront of the development of fresh-fish processing in Canada; and today it is the base for Canada's largest fish-processing plant and fleet of deep-sea trawlers. Lunenburg was, and remains, an important centre for shipbuilding and related industries. It is one Of the very few communities in North America Where traditional shipbuilding Skills are still to be found.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/741</http_url>
<id_number>741</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_741.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>44.3761111100</latitude><location>Nova Scotia</location>
<longitude>-64.3091666700</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Lunenburg is a remarkably well-preserved town, and one which retains most of the qualities of the original British model colonial settlement, without losing its status as a fully functioning community in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The narrow peninsula on which Lunenburg was built was first settled formally in 1753, when German, Swiss and Montb&amp;eacute;liardian French immigrants were brought to Nova Scotia under a British colonization plan. A rigid gridiron plan was superimposed on the slope of the steep hill rising up from the harbour. The new settlement was named Lunenburg after the Royal House of Brunswick-Luneberg, from which the Hanoverian kings of England were descended. The 1453 largely German-speaking Protestants who migrated to Lunenburg in 1752-53 represent the most northerly German settlement in North America in the 18th century. German customs and the German language survived an unusually long time in Lunenburg, owing to its relative isolation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Lunenburg was the second British colonial 'model' town plan, after Halifax (1749). The model town was an important aspect of imperial policy for the British, to provide the functional space thought necessary for the smooth working of a colony. The Lunenburg plan (1753) incorporated all the principles of the model town: geometrically regular streets and blocks; the allocation of public spaces; an allowance for fortifications; and a distinction between urban and non-urban areas. Of these all but the fortifications survive in present-day Lunenburg.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The layout of the existing town preserves almost in its entirety the model layout of the mid-18th century. The plan consisted of six divisions of eight blocks each, each block being in turn subdivided into fourteen lots. Each settler was given a town lot and a larger 'garden lot' outside the town limits. One section of the town was not divided into lots, to serve as a public parade ground.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The town site, true to then-current convention, consisted of seven north-south streets, 12.5&amp;nbsp;m wide (with the exception of King Street, which is 24.4&amp;nbsp;m wide), intersected at right angles by nine east-west streets, each 12.2&amp;nbsp;m wide, creating blocks that were further divided into 14 lots of 12.2&amp;nbsp;m by 18.3&amp;nbsp;m.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The architectural stock of Lunenburg's Old Town is remarkably homogeneous and cohesive. Over 95% of the buildings are built from wood, many of them using the coulisse construction technique that is uncommon in North America.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The founding period in the 18th century is represented by at least eight buildings of &lt;em&gt;coulisse&lt;/em&gt; construction (wooden frames in-filled with horizontal planks). They were built close to one another and to the streets, with the wider elevation facing the harbour. Two-thirds of the buildings of Lunenburg date from the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The earlier examples continue the 18th-century tradition. The pattern of construction of the residential buildings is repeated in the commercial and waterfront buildings, where wood predominates. The same applies to the churches: the second oldest protestant church building in Canada, St John's Anglican Church, begun in 1754, is considered by experts to be an example of 'Carpenter Gothic' at its finest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Given the innate conservatism of the inhabitants of the town with respect to their houses, and taking account of the care being taken to restore historic houses to their original states, the level of authenticity is high on every count. The setting and layout of the town itself have changed minimally since 1753, only the defences having been demolished. Wood remains overwhelming the principal construction material and traditional techniques have been maintained when restoration has been carried out on earlier buildings.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Lunenburg is the best surviving example of a planned British colonial settlement in North America. Established in 1753, it has retained its original layout and overall appearance, based on a rectangular grid pattern drawn up in the home country. The inhabitants have managed to safeguard the city's identity throughout the centuries by preserving the wooden architecture of the houses, some of which date from the 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Old Town Lunenburg</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>875</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(i)(iv)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>2007</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;As a result of the American War of Independence, thousands of people who remained loyal to the British Crown moved northwards to Canada. The government immediately began identifying areas suitable for the development of settlements for the loyalists. The Cataraqui and the Rideau rivers was one of the areas surveyed and by 1800, a number of mills had been built, the first, at Kingston Mills, in 1784. Within a few years, there were mills at most of the major falls along the two rivers. However the difficulty of navigation along the rivers north to the St Lawrence river, the main settlement area, hindered much concentrated development.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The impetus to improve the waterway came though not from agriculture or other economic stimuli but from the needs of defence. The War of 1812-1814 between Britain and the United States of America had brought into focus the vulnerability of the St Lawrence River as the main supply line for the colony. Not only was it slow with a series of rapids, but it was vulnerable to attack from America along much of its length between Montr&amp;eacute;al and Lake Ontario. After the end of hostilities, America was still seen as a potential threat and the need for a secure military supply route a key necessity. Accordingly military planners turned their attention to the Cataraqui and the Rideau rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;After an exploratory mission, at the end of the war, the canal project was really launched in 1824-1825, with two studies, one by the civil engineer Samuel Clowes, at the request of the authorities of Upper Canada, and the other at the request of the Duke of Wellington, then commander-in- chief of the army. The strategic dimension of the canal led the British government to take charges of its realisation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel John By of the Royal Engineers Corp was appointed by the British Government to supervise the construction of the canal in 1826. Before his appointment, military engineers had mapped out a scheme to construct new channels to bypass the rapids and swamps along the rivers. This would have necessitated around 40km of new channels along the 202 km route. By took a different approach and persuaded the government to adopt a &amp;lsquo;slackwater' system that raised the level of the water above the rapids and swamps thorough the use of tall dams. This created a practical route with the minimum of excavation. By also pressed for the canal to accommodate the then newly introduced steamships and this necessitated dams that were taller and wider than anything previously constructed in North America. Canal construction begun in 1828 and involved around 6,000 workers at multiple sites along the length of the canal. The whole length was navigable in 1832.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The choice of route for the Rideau Canal, and the use of a slack water canal design, were influenced by the underdeveloped nature of the country through which the canal was to pass. In many parts of Europe, for instance, owners of riverside agricultural land, water mills and fishing rights would have resisted the alteration in river levels required by such a system. Slackwater canals are easier to build, and require fewer workers. Therefore this method will be chosen instead of a more costly conventional canal where the environment allows, as was the case with the Rideau Canal.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;As with many canals, the Rideau Canal seems to have formed a catalyst for development. Ottawa grew around the canal as it runs southward from the Ottawa River, and elsewhere towns sprung up on the canal's banks. This is typical of economic development associated with canals, and mirrors the development of towns following canal building elsewhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Rideau Canal has survived almost in its original condition as it was by-passed following the improvement in relations between Britain and the USA and the development of the much larger St Lawrence Seaway. Its military capacity was never put to the test. It now functions mainly as a waterway for leisure craft.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1221</http_url>
<id_number>1221</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1221.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>44.9943861111</latitude><location>Province of Ontario</location>
<longitude>-75.7651250000</longitude>
<long_description></long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The Rideau Canal, a monumental early 19th-century construction covering 202 km of the Rideau and Cataraqui rivers from Ottawa south to Kingston Harbour on Lake Ontario, was built primarily for strategic military purposes at a time when Great Britain and the United States vied for control of the region. The site, one of the first canals to be designed specifically for steam-powered vessels, also features an ensemble of fortifications. It is the best-preserved example of a slackwater canal in North America, demonstrating the use of this European technology on a large scale. It is the only canal dating from the great North American canal-building era of the early 19th century to remain operational along its original line with most of its structures intact.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Rideau Canal</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>1475</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>2008</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1285</http_url>
<id_number>1285</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1285.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>45.7097222222</latitude><location></location>
<longitude>-64.4358333333</longitude>
<long_description></long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The Joggins Fossil Cliffs, a 689 ha palaeontological site along the coast of Nova Scotia (eastern Canada), have been described as the &amp;ldquo;coal age Gal&amp;aacute;pagos&amp;rdquo; due to their wealth of fossils from the Carboniferous period (354 to 290 million years ago). The rocks of this site are considered to be iconic for this period of the history of Earth and are the world&amp;rsquo;s thickest and most comprehensive record of the Pennsylvanian strata (dating back 318 to 303 million years) with the most complete known fossil record of terrestrial life from that time. These include the remains and tracks of very early animals and the rainforest in which they lived, left in situ, intact and undisturbed. With its 14.7 km of sea cliffs, low bluffs, rock platforms and beach, the site groups remains of three ecosystems: estuarine bay, floodplain rainforest and fire prone forested alluvial plain with freshwater pools. It offers the richest assemblage known of the fossil life in these three ecosystems with 96 genera and 148 species of fossils and 20 footprint groups. The site is listed as containing outstanding examples representing major stages in the history of Earth.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Joggins Fossil Cliffs</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>1516</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(v)(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>2012</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p align="left"&gt;Since the 1680s, when a small group of Acadian settlers first arrived in the area and called the vast wetlands la grand pr&amp;eacute;, the human history of Grand Pr&amp;eacute; has been linked to its natural setting and the exceptional fertility of this land by the sea. The earliest settlers were isolated. They were a long way from home and were mostly ignored by the various French and British authorities who administered the area. The settlers developed close relations with the local Mi&amp;rsquo;kmaq, the indigenous people of Nova Scotia &amp;ndash; not just at Grand Pr&amp;eacute; but elsewhere in Acadie &amp;ndash; as they came to grips with the natural setting and began to claim fertile land from the sea by building dykes. All of these factors contributed to their developing a new and distinct identity. Though French by birth, over the course of the second half of the 17th century they came to see themselves as belonging to l&amp;rsquo;Acadie, as being Acadiens and Acadiennes. During the roughly 70 years before their forcible removal in 1755, the Acadian community of Grand Pr&amp;eacute; introduced an environmental management approach that had been applied elsewhere in Acadie. Acadians took European&amp;nbsp; practices, developed for wetlands and saltpans, and adapted them to the much different environment in Acadie. Faced with the highest recorded tides in the world, the Acadians at Grand Pr&amp;eacute; worked for three generations to transform over 1300 hectares of tidal marsh into farmland. The farmland was then &amp;ndash; and remains today &amp;ndash; some of the finest farmland in North America. In 1760, fi ve years after the Acadians were fi rst deported from Grand Pr&amp;eacute; and dispersed throughout the world, a contingent of New England Planters was settled at Grand Pr&amp;eacute; to take over the lands. Then, as now, the transformed marsh was the primary focus for the area&amp;rsquo;s inhabitants. Like the Acadians before them, the New England Planters in the Grand Pr&amp;eacute; area developed their own strong connections to the land and their rural way of life. The Grand Pr&amp;eacute; dykeland remains highly fertile today, and the most important features of the original dyked area remain in place. Then, beginning in the late 19th century and continuing until today, Grand Pr&amp;eacute; developed as the most important lieu de m&amp;eacute;moire of the Acadian people. Memorials and commemorative gardens were created adjacent to the transformed marsh to mark the ancient Acadian settlement, commemorate the removal of the people in 1755, and celebrate the vitality of the Acadian community. This last transformation completed the symbolic reclamation by the Acadians of an agricultural land from which they had been forcibly removed.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1404</http_url>
<id_number>1404</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1404.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>ca</iso_code>
<justification>&lt;p align="left"&gt;The Landscape of Grand Pr&amp;eacute; is an outstanding example and enduring model of the human capacity to overcome extraordinary natural challenges and cultural ordeals.&lt;/p&gt;</justification>
<latitude>45.1183333333</latitude><location></location>
<longitude>-64.3072222222</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p align="left"&gt;The nominated property consists of 1323 hectares of dykelands, known elsewhere as polders, and uplands on the southern edge of the Minas Basin, an eastern arm of the Bay of Fundy in western mainland Nova Scotia. It is bordered by the Gaspereau River to the east, the Cornwallis River to the west, Long Island to the north, and parts of the communities of Grand Pr&amp;eacute;, Hortonville, and Lower Wolfville to the south. Dominating the distant background, beyond the nominated property, Cape Blomidon extends into the basin as an instantly recognizable landmark. The nominated property includes the dykeland area that the Acadians created in the 17th century, which successive generations of farmers have expanded. It also includes distinctive representative sections of the Acadian settlement and of the current agricultural community, as well as the entire planned settlement for the New England Planters, a British town grid. No clear historical record marks the boundaries of the 17th and 18th century community of Grand Pr&amp;eacute;. In fact, historical accounts and maps alternately use the names Grand-Pr&amp;eacute; and Les Mines to refer to the general area next to the Minas Basin and to the reclaimed marsh between the Rivi&amp;egrave;re-aux-Canards (Canard River) and the Rivi&amp;egrave;re Gaspareau (Gaspereau River). Even so, other records attest to the presence of the Acadian settlement on the uplands portion of the nominated property. The heart of the Acadian settlement is now defi ned by a concentration of archaeological remains of houses, fi eld patterns, the cemetery, the traditional location of the remains of the parish church of Saint-Charles-des-Mines, and the intersection of main roads. The southeast corner of the nominated property includes the surviving evidence of the planned British town grid in Hortonville. The grid is defi ned by Railway Street, King Street, and Middle Street running east&amp;ndash;west and by Horton Cross Road, Wharf Road, and Patterson Street running north&amp;ndash;south. Today, the agricultural community surrounds the dykelands and extends over the hills to the Gaspereau River. The nominated property includes the heart of the Acadian settlement and the British town grid. Since the time of the fi rst Acadian settlement in the 17th century, people have continuously worked these dykelands. The property also includes parts of the hamlet of Grand Pr&amp;eacute;, which hosts provincially and municipally designated heritage properties and some local services, plus farms on the hills and an expanse of fi elds and pastures. At the heart of both the nominated property and the Acadian settlement lies Grand-Pr&amp;eacute; National Historic Site of Canada. The national historic site consists of the commemorative gardens, the Memorial Church, cemeteries, and many other memorials to the Acadian Deportation. Through tangible and intangible evidence, this exceptional landscape illustrates the harsh environment, the genius of the dyking system, the productivity of the farmland, and its symbolic reclamation by the Acadian people.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated in the southern Minas Basin of Nova Scotia, the Grand Pr&amp;eacute; marshland and archaeological sites constitute a cultural landscape bearing testimony to the development of agricultural farmland using dykes and the &lt;em&gt;aboiteau &lt;/em&gt;wooden sluice system, started by the Acadians in the 17th century and further developed and maintained by the Planters and present-day inhabitants. Over 1,300&amp;nbsp;ha, the cultural landscape encompasses a large expanse of polder farmland and archaeological elements of the towns of Grand Pr&amp;eacute; and Hortonville, which were built by the Acadians and their successors. The landscape is an exceptional example of the adaptation of the first European settlers to the conditions of the North American Atlantic coast. The site &amp;ndash; marked by one of the most extreme tidal ranges in the world, averaging 11.6&amp;nbsp;m &amp;ndash; is also inscribed as a memorial to Acadian way of life and deportation, which started in 1755, known as the &lt;em&gt;Grand D&amp;eacute;rangement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Landscape of Grand Pré</site>
<states>Canada</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>1828</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1978</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/27</http_url>
<id_number>27</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_27.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>37.2616666700</latitude><location>Colorado</location>
<longitude>-108.4855556000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Among the American Indian civilizations recognized by ethnologists and prehistorians, that of the Anasazi Indians and of their distant descendants, the Pueblos of New Mexico and Arizona are indeed quite original, owing in part to the substantial rigours of their natural environment: the south-western part of Colorado with its mesas cut by deep canyons. On the high limestone and sandstone plateau, which in one place reaches an altitude of 2,620&amp;nbsp;m above sea level, the climate is semi-arid, being characterized by irregular precipitation and great differences between day and night temperature. The first signs of regular human occupation go back to the 6th century of the current era. They are principally located on the plateau where partially buried villages, consisting of silos and low dwellings, have existed since this period. Original handicrafts, in which the production of yucca fibre objects play a major role, was to remain characteristic of Anasazi civilization for seven centuries.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;From roughly 750 to 1100 some highly specific features appeared in the human settlements of Mesa Verde. While the plateau villages were increasingly built in an L- or U-shaped layout, the valley villages grew larger. In rock shelters under the refuge of imposing overhanging cliffs, on the side of cuestas deeply lacerated by erosion, composite, both troglodytic and built villages were established having various functions: agricultural, handicrafts or religious - the first &lt;em&gt;kivas&lt;/em&gt; (subterranean or buried structures of a subcircular layout) appeared during this period.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;This civilization reached its apogee between 1100 and the end of the 13th century before suddenly disappearing. Impressive, multi-storey constructions (the best-known being 'Cliff Palace' and 'Long House', with its 181 rooms and 15 &lt;em&gt;kivas&lt;/em&gt;) were erected under the shelter of the cliffs. They are demonstrative of surprising progress in building techniques and a very keen sense for use of space. At the same time, agrarian techniques were improved: irrigation, based on a network of reservoirs and dams, was used to offset the rigours of a climate largely hostile to the cultivation of cereals and starches, staples of the Anasazi diet. This 'golden age', facilitated by control of the natural environment, is further illustrated by the outstanding quality of the handicrafts. As the first explorers of Mesa Verde claimed on many an occasion, the wickerwork, weaving and especially ceramics were of astonishing quality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Discovered in 1874, the rock-cut villages of Mesa Verde were pillaged by collectors (there was a very large pottery sale in 1889) before being studied and excavated by archaeologists. However, the protection of the site which came into effect in 1906 under the Federal Antiquities Act is one of the most effective and long-standing on the American continent.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;A great concentration of ancestral Pueblo Indian dwellings, built from the 6th to the 12th century, can be found on the Mesa Verde plateau in south-west Colorado at an altitude of more than 2,600 m. Some 4,400 sites have been recorded, including villages built on the Mesa top. There are also imposing cliff dwellings, built of stone and comprising more than 100 rooms.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Mesa Verde National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>30</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger>P 1995-2003</danger>
<date_inscribed>1978</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Created a national park on 1 March 1872; accepted as a biosphere reserve in June 1976; and accepted as a World Heritage site in 1978. Protection is provided under several congressional acts.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/28</http_url>
<id_number>28</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_28.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>44.4605600000</latitude><location>Northwest corner of the State of Wyoming and relatively small adjacent areas of the States of Montana and Idaho</location>
<longitude>-110.8277800000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Yellowstone National Park, established in 1872, covers 9,000&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of a vast natural forest of the southern Rocky Mountains in the North American west. It boasts an impressive array of geothermal phenomena, with more than 3,000 geysers, lava formations, fumaroles, hot springs and waterfalls, lakes and canyons. It is equally known for its wildlife: grizzly bears, bison, wolves and wapiti, North American elk.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is part of the most seismically active region of the Rocky Mountains, a volcanic 'hot spot'. The Yellowstone Plateau, now a forested area of 650,000&amp;nbsp;ha with an average elevation of 2,000&amp;nbsp;m, was formed out of the accumulation of rhyolite magma. The plateau is flanked on the north, east and south by mountains that rise to 4,000&amp;nbsp;m. Crustal uplifts 65&amp;nbsp;million years ago raised blocks of crust to form the southern Rocky Mountains. After that, volcanic outflows of andesitic composition were common to about 40&amp;nbsp;million years ago. Andesitic ashflows and mudflows of the Eocene age covered forests, which became petrified. Some 200 species of petrified plant have been found. A more recent period of rhyolitic volcanism began in the region about 2&amp;nbsp;million years ago, during which time thousands of cubic kilometres of rhyolitic magma filled immense chambers under the plateau and then erupted to the surface. Three cycles of eruption produced huge explosive outbursts of ash. The latest eruptive cycle formed a caldera 45&amp;nbsp;km wide and 75&amp;nbsp;km long, when the active magma chambers erupted and collapsed. The crystallizing magma is the source of heat for hydrothermal features such as geysers, hot springs, mud pots and fumaroles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Yellowstone contains 200-250 active geysers and perhaps 10,000 thermal features. Most of the area was glaciated during the Pleistocene and many glacial features remain. The park lies at the headwaters of three major rivers. Yellowstone River is a major tributary of the Missouri River that flows via the Mississippi to the Gulf of Mexico. Firehole and Gibbon rivers unite to form the Madison, which also joins the Missouri. Snake River arises near the park's south boundary and joins the Columbia to flow into the Pacific. Yellowstone Lake is the largest lake at high elevation (2,357&amp;nbsp;m) in North America. Lower Yellowstone Falls is the highest of more than 40 named waterfalls in the park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is dominated by lodgepole pine. Great elevational differences produce a range of plant communities, from semi-arid steppe to alpine tundra. There are seven species of coniferous tree and some 1,100 species of vascular plant growing in the park, including an endemic grass. The thermal areas contain unique assemblages of thermal algae and bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Six species of ungulate are native to the park. Grizzly bear has been the subject of intensive study and management for 30 years. There are currently some 50 breeding females and 150 cubs have been born in the last three years. Native fishes are protected by regulations that also permit the taking of non-native introduced species.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Palaeontological study of Lamar Cave has yielded remains of over 30 species of mammal. This suggests a diversity of fauna in prehistoric times much like that found in Yellowstone today.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological investigations of numerous important sites show that human groups visited the park area for 10,000 years, but none made it a permanent home.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The vast natural forest of Yellowstone National Park covers nearly 9,000 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ; 96% of the park lies in Wyoming, 3% in Montana and 1% in Idaho. Yellowstone contains half of all the world's known geothermal features, with more than 10,000 examples. It also has the world's largest concentration of geysers (more than 300 geyers, or two thirds of all those on the planet). Established in 1872, Yellowstone is equally known for its wildlife, such as grizzly bears, wolves, bison and wapitis.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Yellowstone National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>31</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1979</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Created a national park on 26 February 1919 by an act of Congress. First protected in 1893 as a forest reserve in which mining, lumbering and hunting continued to be allowed; upgraded to a game reserve in 1906, giving protection to the wildlife; redesignated a national monument in 1908. Accepted as a World Heritage site on 24 October _979.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/75</http_url>
<id_number>75</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_75.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>36.1008333300</latitude><location>Counties of Coconino and Mohave in the State of Arizona</location>
<longitude>-112.0905556000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Grand Canyon National Park was created on 26 February 1919 by an act of Congress. First protected in 1893 as a forest reserve in which mining, lumbering and hunting continued to be allowed: upgraded to a game reserve in 1906, giving protection to the wildlife: redesignated a National Monument in 1908.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is dominated by the spectacular Grand Canyon: a twisting, 1.5&amp;nbsp;km deep and 445.8&amp;nbsp;km long gorge, formed during some 6&amp;nbsp;million years of geological activity and erosion by the Colorado River on the raised Earth's crust (2.5&amp;nbsp;km above sea level). It divides the park into the North Rim and South Rim which overlook the 200&amp;nbsp;m to 30&amp;nbsp;km wide canyon; the buttes, spires, mesas and temples in the canyon are in fact mountains looked down upon from the rims. Ongoing erosion by the seasonal and permanent rivers produces impressive waterfalls and rapids of washed-down boulders along the length of the canyon and its tributaries. Exposed horizontal geological strata in the canyon span some 2,000&amp;nbsp;million years of geological history, providing evidence of the four major geological eras, early and late Precambrian, Palaeozoic, Mesozoic and Cenozoic. The early Precambrian strata, known as the Vishnu Schist formation, are devoid of fossils. The first fossil evidence appears in the late Precambrian Bass Limestone with remains of early plant forms. Subsequent strata dating from the Palaeozoic era catalogue the sequence of local history, with both marine and terrestrial fossils demonstrating the periods in the distant past when the whole region was alternately submerged and raised. The Mesozoic era is less well illustrated within the park, but tracks made by early reptiles are found to the east in the Navajo Indian reservation. They are a few fossil remains of mammals from the early Cenozoic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Altitudinal range provides a variety of climates and habitats, ranging from desert to mountain conditions. The canyon is a vast biological museum stretching through five different life and vegetation zones: Hudsonian on the North Rim plateau with Colorado blue spruce and Rocky Mountain maple; Canadian near the North Rim, with aspen and Ponderosa and forests of Douglas fir, white fir and aspen at 2,500&amp;nbsp;m; high-altitude Transition (Ponderosa) forests of &lt;em&gt;Pinus ponderosa&lt;/em&gt; and gambel oak; upper Sonoran on and below the South Rim with Utah juniper, pinon pine and sagebrush; and the Lower Sonoran down the canyon and at the bottom (desert cacti, rabbitbrush, mesquite, Morman tea and Manzanita).&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Over 1,000 plant species have so far been identified from the park. There are 11 plant species listed as threatened in the United States statutes in the park, including Palmer amsonia, goldenweed, plains cactus, scouler catchfly, wild buckwheats, primrose and clute penstemon. In addition, 15 plant species are recommended for consideration as threatened species under the Endangered Species Act.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Concerning the fauna, 76 mammal, 299 bird and 41 reptile and amphibian species have been identified from the park and some 16 fish species inhabit the Colorado River and its tributaries. Rare or threatened birds are listed under the United States Endangered Species Act of 1973.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park contains more than 2,600 documented prehistoric ruins, including evidence of Archaic cultures (the earliest known inhabitants), Cohonina Indians along the South Rim, and Anasazi Indians on both the South Rim, North Rim, and within the Inner Canyon. Hualapai and Havasupai Indians moved into the canyons at this time, where they remained undisturbed until the Anglo-Americans arrived in 1860. Archaeological remains show the adaptation of human societies to severe climate and physiographic environment.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Carved out by the Colorado River, the Grand Canyon (nearly 1,500 m deep) is the most spectacular gorge in the world. Located in the state of Arizona, it cuts across the Grand Canyon National Park. Its horizontal strata retrace the geological history of the past 2 billion years. There are also prehistoric traces of human adaptation to a particularly harsh environment.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Grand Canyon National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>81</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger>Y 2010 P 1993-2007</danger>
<date_inscribed>1979</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Declared a national park on 6 December 1947 under the May 1934 Act of Congress. The park was accepted as a biosphere reserve in 1976, inscribed on the World Heritage List in 1979, and was designated a Ramsar site (Wetland of International Significance) in 1987. The total area of the national park was increased in 1989 from its original size of 566, 788ha to its current size.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/76</http_url>
<id_number>76</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_76.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>25.5544444400</latitude><location>Southern tip of the Florida peninsula, along the Gulf of Mexico, State of Florida</location>
<longitude>-80.9963888900</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Everglades National Park is situated on the southern tip of the Florida Peninsula. The park is bounded by the Gulf of Mexico to the west, the Tamiami Trail and mostly state lands to the north and the Florida Keys to the south and south-east. It includes most of Florida Bay. The biosphere reserve includes Dry Tortugas National Park, a group of seven coral reefs and surrounding shoals, coral reefs and waters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Everglades National Park is a shallow basin tilted to the south-west and underlain by extensive Pleistocene limestone with oolitic and bryozoan facies. The park serves as a vital recharge area for the Biscayne Aquifer, a major source of freshwater for Miami and south-east Florida. It lies at the interface between temperate and subtropical America and between fresh and brackish water, shallow bays and deeper coastal waters, thus creating a complex of habitats supporting a high diversity of flora and fauna. The area of transition from freshwater (glades) to saltwater (mangrove) is a highly productive zone that incubates great numbers of economically valuable crustacea. The vegetation and flora of south Florida have fascinated scientists and naturalists since their discovery and were a primary reason for the establishment of the park. One cause of this fascination is the presence of a high percentage of West Indian species. A noteworthy feature is the rather high degree of local endemism. Hammocks or tree islands are dominated by hardwood species of both tropical and temperate affinities. The most important trees are mangroves, taxa, slash pine and cypress. Prairies can be dominated by sawgrass, muhley grass, or cordgrass in coastal areas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Everglades protect 800 species of land and water vertebrates, including over 14 threatened species, and 25 mammals, over 400 bird species, 60 known species of reptile, amphibian and insect, including two threatened swallowtail butterfly species. Over 20 species of snake have been recorded, including the threatened indigo snake. More than 275 species of fish are known from the Everglades, most inhabiting the marine and estuarine waters. Several species are important game species that attract thousands of anglers to the park. During autumn a continuous procession of songbirds and other migrants fly over or rest on these islands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is rich in both prehistoric and historic heritage: it contains 200 known archaeological sites. A Native American group, the Miccosukee tribe of Florida, has a special use permit area inside the park. Fort Jefferson, in Dry Tortugas National Park, is the largest brick masonry fort in America. It was large enough to garrison 1,500 men, but was never involved in battle, although it did secure a post for Union forces during the Civil War and afterwards served as a prison. The park's northern boundary is retained by the Miccosukee Indians under a special use permit for community development.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;This site at the southern tip of Florida has been called 'a river of grass flowing imperceptibly from the hinterland into the sea'. The exceptional variety of its water habitats has made it a sanctuary for a large number of birds and reptiles, as well as for threatened species such as the manatee.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Everglades National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>82</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1979</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/78</http_url>
<id_number>78</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_78.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>39.9486111100</latitude><location>Philadelphia, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania</location>
<longitude>-75.1500000000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Independence Hall in Philadelphia may be considered the birthplace of the United States of America: it was here that the Declaration of Independence was signed in 1776, the Articles of Confederation uniting the 13 colonies were ratified in 1781, and the Constitution setting out the nation's basic laws was adopted in 1787, after George Washington had presided over the debate, which ran from May to September.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The building was designed by Andrew Hamilton to house the Assembly of the Commonwealth (colony) of Pennsylvania. Finished in 1753, it is a modest brick structure with a steeple that was intended to hold a 2,080&amp;nbsp;lb (943&amp;nbsp;kg) bell. The bell, however, has cracked twice and stands silently on the ground in a special shelter (a reproduction now hangs in the steeple). Independence Hall is important not for its architectural design but for the documents of fundamental importance to American history drafted and debated here that formed the democracy of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The building has undergone many restorations, notably by Greek revival architect John Haviland in 1830, and by a committee from the National Park Service in 1950, returning it to its 1776 appearance. The universal principles of freedom and democracy have also had a profound impact on lawmakers around the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Independence National Historical Park, located in downtown Philadelphia ('Centre City'), interprets events and the lives of the diverse population during the years when the city was the capital of the United States, from 1790 to 1800. A section of the park where Benjamin Franklin's home once stood is dedicated to teaching about his life and accomplishments. Spanning approximately 18&amp;nbsp;ha, the park has about 20 buildings open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;The Declaration of Independence (1776) and the Constitution of the United States (1787) were both signed in this building in Philadelphia. The universal principles of freedom and democracy set forth in these documents are of fundamental importance to American history and have also had a profound impact on law-makers around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Independence Hall</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>84</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(ix)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1980</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;2 October 1968, under Public Law 90-545, when three existing state parks were fused with the addition of about 11,340ha of privately owned land with 19,440ha added 27 March 1978. Inscribed on the World Heritage list in 1980. Comprises part of California Coastal Ranges Biosphere Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/134</http_url>
<id_number>134</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_134.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>41.3738888900</latitude><location>California</location>
<longitude>-123.9980556000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Redwood National Park comprises a region of coastal mountains bordering the Pacific (to 930&amp;nbsp;m above sea level) north of San Francisco. It is covered with a magnificent forest of sequoia redwood trees, the tallest and most impressive trees in the world. The marine and land life are equally remarkable, in particular the sea lions, the bald eagle and the endangered California brown pelican.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park was established specifically to protect these trees, because it is only here and in Oregon that they now survive. Descendants of the giant evergreens that grew during the age of the dinosaurs, redwoods thrived in moist temperate regions of the world. They take 400 years to mature and some of the survivors are more than 2,000 years old. Their thick, sapless bark protects them from fire, but landslides and wind can topple old trees. Cultural landscapes reflect American Indian history. The Indians used fallen redwood trees to build canoes and houses; commercial logging began during the gold rush era. Logging of redwoods continues and is debated by the timber industry and environmentalists. The trees stand as majestic reminders of the slow evolution of nature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The area transcends two distinctive physiographic environments: the coastline, and the mountains of the Coast Range. The park's 55&amp;nbsp;km coastline consists of steep, rocky cliffs broken by rolling slopes and broad sandy beaches. Gently rounded summits contrast with steep slopes and deeply incised streams. Bedrock is primarily highly deformed Cretaceous deep water marine sandstones, siltstones and shales. Lesser amounts of chert, volcanic greenstones and metamorphic rocks occur as blocks within the sedimentary rocks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The predominant vegetation type is coastal redwood forest. There are 15,800&amp;nbsp;ha of old-growth redwood, 20,800&amp;nbsp;ha are cut over and the balance comprises other vegetation types. The redwoods are surviving remnants of the group of trees that were once found throughout many of the moist temperate regions of the world, but are now confined to the wet regions on the west coast of North America. As slope and dryness increase, the forest is superseded by prairie vegetation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are 75 species of mammal. Freshwater marshes, ponds and streams provide valuable nesting and feeding areas for several species of migratory waterfowl. Several offshore rocks in the area are important nesting sites for seabirds. Threatened birds include the endangered brown pelican, southern bald eagle and American falcon.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological surveys, test excavations, research and consultations conducted over the past 20 years have resulted in the recording of 50 prehistoric archaeological sites, 19 historic sites and at least 21 places of significance to local Indian communities. The archaeological sites span 4,500 years and represent changing settlement and subsistence systems. Historic resources include examples of early trails, homestead and ranching, fishing, dairy, mining and logging industries, and military structure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The redwood forests represent some 42% of the remaining old growth redwood stands, a small fragment of once extensive cover. Legal protection is total, but sport fishing is allowed. The principal National Park Service zoning classification comprises natural, historic and park development enclaves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The parks' mosaic of habitats includes prairie/oak woodlands, mighty rivers and streams and 55&amp;nbsp;km of pristine Pacific coastline.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Redwood National Park comprises a region of coastal mountains bordering the Pacific Ocean north of San Francisco. It is covered with a magnificent forest of coastal redwood trees, the tallest and most impressive trees in the world. The marine and land life are equally remarkable, in particular the sea lions, the bald eagle and the endangered California brown pelican.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Redwood National and State Parks</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>147</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1981</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;The area was declared a national park on 1 July 1941, under enabling legislation of US Congress (44 Statute 635) of 25 May 1926. Kentucky ceded exclusive jurisdiction over park lands by an act of legislature approved on 22 March 1930 and this was accepted by the Secretary of the Interior on 1 May 1944 by authority of the act of 5 June 1942 (56 Statute 317). Exclusive jurisdiction over the remainder of the land was accepted on 1 May 1965. Certain roads through the park are legally open to the public under Deed No.262 of 18 June 1945. Part of the area is endorsed by the Barren River Area Development District resolution of 24 October 1988. Big Woods Old-growth Forest is designated a state natural area by the state of Kentucky. Green River is designated a wild and scenic river and Green River and Mammoth Cave subsurface streams are designated outstanding resource waters by this state. Accepted as a World Heritage site in 1981 and as a biosphere reserve in 1990.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/150</http_url>
<id_number>150</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_150.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>37.1872222200</latitude><location>Counties of Barren, Edmonson, and Hart in the State of Kentucky</location>
<longitude>-86.1030555600</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Mammoth Cave National Park, located in the state of Kentucky, has the world's largest network of natural caves and underground passageways, which are characteristic examples of limestone formations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park includes by far the longest cave system in the world, with known passages extending some 550&amp;nbsp;km. It is of geological importance due to the 25&amp;nbsp;million years of cave-forming action by the Green River and its tributaries. Almost every type of cave formation is known within the site and the geological processes involved in cave formation are continuing. The long passages with huge chambers, vertical shafts, stalagmites and stalactites, gypsum 'flowers' and 'needles' and other natural features of the cave system are all superlative examples of their types. The park and its underground network of more than 550&amp;nbsp;km surveyed passageways are home to varied flora and fauna (including a number of endangered species).&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;It is the most extensive and diverse cave ecosystem in the world, with over 200 species, mostly invertebrate, indigenous to the network of caves, with 42 species adapted to life in total darkness. Outside the cave, the karst topography is superb, with fascinating landscapes, luxuriant vegetation and abundant wildlife - terrestrial vertebrates include 43 mammal, 207 bird, 37 reptile and 27 amphibian species. All the features of a karst drainage system are found within the site. Fossils are distributed throughout the rocks of the Mississippian age and include brachiopods, crinoids and corals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Surface features are also important and Big Woods, a temperate deciduous oak-hickory dominated forest, is reputed to be one of the largest and best remaining examples of the ancient forest of eastern North America that once covered Kentucky. The vegetation communities on the surface of the plateau include 84 tree varieties, 28 varieties of shrubs and vines, 29 types of fern, 209 wildflowers, 67 species of algae, 27 species of fungi and 7 species of bryophyte. This temperate deciduous oak-hickory forest is dominated by oaks including white, black and chestnut oaks and hickories including pignut and mockernut, with some beech, maples, tulip tree, ash and eastern red cedar&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The troglodyte fauna includes several endangered species of blind fish, shrimp, bat and freshwater mussel.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Of special concern is the Kentucky cave shrimp, a freshwater species of uncertain status. The geological setting has contributed to the species richness of the area with the cave system being old enough to have viable communities of fauna from three karst regions within an area large enough for speciation to have occurred. Nowhere else do the blind fish and their spring-cave dwelling relative co-exist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological sites in the area show evidence of four pre-Columbian Indian cultures. Mammoth Cave has been important in the development of human culture, with four distinct cultural periods described: palaeo-Indian, Archaic, Woodland and Mississippian. The early Woodland culture is particularly important because it marked the independent development of organized horticulture in the Western Hemisphere, with primitive agriculture on river floodplains and was the period of the first exploration and mining in Mammoth Cave. Several mummies, sandals, campfire sites, bare foot prints have been found preserved in the stabilizing cave atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;However, the site does not include the entire river catchments of waters flowing through the site, so future disturbance is possible, particularly to the south and east of the park, where light industry is replacing agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are no permanent inhabitants in the core area. About 240 people live in the buffer zones with a further 1,500 in the transition area, including about 600 in Park City.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Mammoth Cave National Park, located in the state of Kentucky, has the world's largest network of natural caves and underground passageways, which are characteristic examples of limestone formations. The park and its underground network of more than 560 surveyed km of passageways are home to a varied flora and fauna, including a number of endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Mammoth Cave National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>168</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(ix)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1981</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;29 June 1938 as a national park; the Pacific Coastal Area and Queets River corridor were added on 6 January 1953. Accepted as a biosphere reserve in June 1976, and as a World Heritage site in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/151</http_url>
<id_number>151</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_151.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>47.7483333300</latitude><location>State of Washington</location>
<longitude>-123.4488889000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Olympic National Park is isolated from other mountain ranges and surrounded by the waters of the Pacific Ocean and Puget Sound; this isolation has allowed the development of endemic species, including Olympic marmot, 4 subspecies of other mammals, 2 subspecies of trout, and 12 species or varieties of plant. 11 major river systems drain the Olympic mountains, offering some of the best habitat for anadromous fish species (such as salmon that live their lives in the sea and migrate to a freshwater river to spawn) in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting the varied topography (from seashore to glacier) and the varied rainfall, the vegetation zones in the site are complex and varied. The park is divided into two segments: a mountainous core and a separate coastal strip. The rugged features of Olympic National Park are the result of the collision of drifting continental plates.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The area contains a great wealth of geological formations, affected by high rainfall on the west and low rainfall on the east. The lighter shales, sandstones and basalts, which had been violently sheared and squeezed during this tectonic movement, bobbed up like a cork, forming a dome some 95&amp;nbsp;km in diameter. Deep valleys and canyons were eroded out of this dome and glaciers sculpted the craggy peaks and beautiful cirques to form the spectacular landscape which characterizes the modern Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The mountains contain about 60 active glaciers; the area is unique in because it is the lowest latitude in the world in which glaciers begin at an elevation lower than 2,000&amp;nbsp;m and exist below 1,000&amp;nbsp;m. Glacier-clad peaks interspersed with extensive alpine meadows are surrounded by an extensive old growth forest, among which is the best example of intact and protected temperate rainforest in the Pacific Northwest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The coastal strip of the site stretches along 80&amp;nbsp;km of wilderness beach, characterized by rocky headlands, log-strewn beaches, and a wealth of intertidal life; rocky islets along the coast are remnants of a continuously receding, changing coastline, and the arches, caves and buttresses are evidence of the continuous battering of the waves. Tide pools are filled with hundreds of species of invertebrate life, and seals, sea lions, sea otters and several species of whale are often seen in the waves and around the offshore islands.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The main danger to the integrity of the site is, oddly, one of its attractions: the mountain goat. Due to the isolation of the site, mountain goats never dispersed naturally to the Olympics, so their introduction in 1925-29 may be causing significant changes in the natural ecosystem. The mountain goats have reduced plant cover, increased erosion, and shifted plant-community dominants towards more resistant or less palatable species; they have been recorded feeding on at least three of the endemic plants, and some concern has been expressed that these species may be endangered by the mountain goat.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The coniferous forest of Olympic is of prime commercial interest and practically all the original forest outside the park has been harvested.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Located in the north-west of Washington State, Olympic National Park is renowned for the diversity of its ecosystems. Glacier-clad peaks interspersed with extensive alpine meadows are surrounded by an extensive old growth forest, among which is the best example of intact and protected temperate rainforest in the Pacific Northwest. Eleven major river systems drain the Olympic mountains, offering some of the best habitat for anadromous fish species in the country. The park also includes 100 km of wilderness coastline, the longest undeveloped coast in the contiguous United States, and is rich in native and endemic animal and plant species, including critical populations of the endangered northern spotted owl, marbled murrelet and bull trout.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Olympic National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>169</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iii)(iv)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1982</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/198</http_url>
<id_number>198</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_198.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>38.6586111100</latitude><location>St. Louis, Illinois</location>
<longitude>-90.0613888900</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Cahokia Mounds State historic site is the most comprehensive affirmation of the pre-Columbian civilizations in the Mississippi region. It is an early and eminent example of pre-urban structuring, which provides an opportunity to study a type of social organization, on which written sources are silent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The archaeological site of Cahokia, so named for a subtribe of the Illini who occupied the area when the French arrived, serves as a point of reference for the study of pre-Columbian civilizations in the area of the Mississippi from approximately 900 to 1600. Within the vast zone of plains and plateaux the occupation of the land and the population development underwent an original evolution during the last phase of prehistory, characterized at once by agricultural advances and by a social system which favoured urban concentration. Anthropologists have estimated a sedentary population of an average of 10,000 inhabitants whose social and professional organization, lifestyle and funerary rites have been brought to light by a series of excavations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Fascinating information about the people who once built the great prehistoric city of Cahokia was revealed accidentally during excavations in the early 1960s. Dr Warren Wittry was studying excavation maps when he observed that numerous large oval-shaped pits seemed to be arranged in arcs of circles. He theorized that posts set in these pits lined up with the rising Sun at certain times of the year, serving as a calendar, which he called Woodhenge. Fragments of wood remaining in some of the post pits revealed that red cedar, a sacred wood, had been used for the posts. The most spectacular sunrise occurs at the equinoxes, when the Sun rises due east. The post marking these sunrises aligns with the front of Monks Mound, where the leader resided, and it looks as though Monks Mound gives birth to the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The limits of the site are defined by a number of earthwork levees comparable to the enceinte of the protohistoric European oppida. Within this circumvallation, space is rationally distributed between living quarters, zones of specialized activities and public ceremonial areas. Small gardens were attached to each living unit but the cultivated lands were essentially found outside the circumvallation, where a series of small satellite villages were located.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The architecture of Cahokia is based on the exclusive use of two materials: earth and wood. The omnipresent forms are those of mounds, when either served as mottes or as funerary tumuli. The dwellings consisted of posts or of wooden palisades. The wooden palisades could serve equally as well as defensive enclosures. In the 12th century, the entire central sector of the site, including the largest (Monks) mound, which is a testament to the sophisticated engineering skills of these people. It had been encircled by such a palisade, which took the form of a bastioned enceinte. Excavation results suggest the existence of a markedly hierarchical social structure, incorporating an interior city where the centre of power was located.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The third circle (AD 1000) was reconstructed in 1985 at the original location. Red ochre pigment found in some of the postholes suggests the posts may have been painted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Associated with Round Top, Mound 60 is a large, rectangular platform mound known as the Fox Mound. These two mounds seem to be united by a platform as a contour line surrounds them both on the map. The contour may, however, only represent a blending of the slope wash, or talus slopes, of the two mounds coming together. They probably were a unit because the relationship to each other is matched by other paired mounds at the site. They seem strongly reminiscent of the association of platform charnel-house mounds and conical burial mounds in this ethno-historic period of the south-eastern United States.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Cahokia Mounds, some 13 km north-east of St Louis, Missouri, is the largest pre-Columbian settlement north of Mexico. It was occupied primarily during the Mississippian period (800&amp;ndash;1400), when it covered nearly 1,600 ha and included some 120 mounds. It is a striking example of a complex chiefdom society, with many satellite mound centres and numerous outlying hamlets and villages. This agricultural society may have had a population of 10&amp;ndash;20,000 at its peak between 1050 and 1150. Primary features at the site include Monks Mound, the largest prehistoric earthwork in the Americas, covering over 5 ha and standing 30 m high.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>219</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1983</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;22 May 1926 as a national park (44 Stat. 616) and June 1976 as a biosphere reserve&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/259</http_url>
<id_number>259</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_259.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>35.5930555600</latitude><location>Counties of Cocke, Blount, and Sevier in the State of Tennessee; and the counties of Swain and Haywood in the state of North Carolina</location>
<longitude>-83.4355555600</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Great Smoky Mountains National Park is the most important natural area in the eastern United States and is of world importance as an example of temperate deciduous hardwood forest and thus an outstanding example of the diverse Arcto-Tertiary geoflora era, having a high number of temperate species with some rich mixed stands. During Pleistocene glaciation it was the major North American refuge for temperate and boreal species of flora and fauna, so has a large number of endemic species as well as an extremely rich species composition. With 130 species of tree, it has almost as many species as all of Europe. This has resulted in a rich vegetation mosaic. It harbours many endangered species of animals, and has possibly the greatest diversity of salamanders in the world; it is a centre of endemism for North American molluscs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The dominant topographic feature of the park is the range of the Great Smoky Mountains with 16 peaks over 1,829m. Lesser ridges form radiating spurs from the central ridgeline. In broad aspect, the topography of the park consists of moderately sharp-crested, steep-sided ridges separated by deep V-shaped valleys. Many of the mountain ridges branch and subdivide creating a complex of drainage systems with many fast-flowing clear mountain streams. The park contains 22 major watersheds and the water table is near the surface in almost all sections. Precambrian metamorphic rocks consisting of gneisses and schists, and sedimentary rocks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The vegetation changes continuously with elevation, slope aspect and soil moisture patterns. Five species are officially listed as endangered on the Fish and Wildlife Service List of Candidate Endangered Plants. A diverse fauna occurs including at least 50 native animals, reflecting the richness of the flora. Several species of bat and over 200 species of bird inhabit the park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy precipitation and numerous streams make the mountains ideal for a wide variety of amphibian species; the park also contains a diversity of invertebrates, over 70 species of native fish, spiders, insects and other arthropods, and over 100 species of caddisfly and stonefly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological sites support the theory that prehistoric people (15,000 years ago) were hunters and gatherers. Present historical and cultural interpretation in the park is based mainly on the structures dating from the mid-1800s to 1920, including the finest collection of log buildings in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park contains evidence of four pre-Columbian Indian cultures: Mississippian, Woodland, Archaic and palaeo-Indian. The early Woodland culture period is of special archaeological importance because it shows the first evidence of organized horticulture in North America, with primitive agriculture on river floodplains. These Indians used the caves for shelters and chipped gypsum and mirabilite off the walls: more than 150 archaeological sites have been identified within the national park. Saltpeter deposits were discovered on the cave walls and this valuable nitrate was removed and sent to be processed in gunpowder factories between 1809 and 1819. Three churches and 14 cemeteries still exist in the park and are used by the public.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are no permanent inhabitants in the core area. About 240 people live in the buffer zones with a further 1,500 in the transition area. Only 25% of the population is considered urban and no significant increase in urbanization is expected in the near future. Most people are engaged in agriculture, tourism or service industries.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Stretching over more than 200,000 ha, this exceptionally beautiful park is home to more than 3,500 plant species, including almost as many trees (130 natural species) as in all of Europe. Many endangered animal species are also found there, including what is probably the greatest variety of salamanders in the world. Since the park is relatively untouched, it gives an idea of temperate flora before the influence of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Great Smoky Mountains National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>289</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1983</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/266</http_url>
<id_number>266</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_266.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>18.4666666700</latitude><location>San Juan, Puerto Rico</location>
<longitude>-66.1250000000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The entire historic site of San Juan with its different monumental components maintains, at the present, a balance between constructed and non-constructed zones. The Fortaleza is tangibly associated with the history of the New World and its explorers and colonists.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;For the explorers and the colonists of the New World who came from the east, Puerto Rico was an obligatory stopping-place in the Caribbean. From this evolved its primordial strategic role at the beginning of the Spanish colonization. The island was for centuries a stake disputed by the Spanish, French, English and Dutch. The fortifications of the bay of San Juan, the magnificent port to which Puerto Rico owes its name, bear witness to its long military history.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;San Juan had the first municipal government in the New World outside Santo Domingo, as well as the first military presidios in Spanish America. By the 19th century, the old city had become a charming residential and commercial district. The city itself, with its institutional buildings, museums, houses, churches, plazas and commercial buildings, is part of the San Juan Historic Zone which is administered by municipal, State and Federal agencies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;La Fortaleza is one among several, of the fortresses which protect it. Over the centuries, San Juan in fact protected Spain's empire against Carib Indians, pirates and the warships of other countries. This vast, coherent defensive system with ramparts, fortlets and fortresses, attesting formerly to its effectiveness and today to its historic significance. The principal components of this defensive system are, starting in the south:&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;ul class="unIndentedList"&gt;&#xd;
&lt;li&gt; La Fortaleza, founded in 1530-40, enlarged at various periods, and heavily modified after 1846, is an exemplary monument of Hispano-American colonial architecture. It served at once as an arsenal, prison, and residence for the Governor-General of the island;&lt;/li&gt;&#xd;
&lt;li&gt; El Morro, built to protect San Juan Bay, is situated on a rocky peak of land on the western extremity of the island. The fort is a triangular bastion perfectly conceived according to the strategy of the second half of the 18th century, when it was entirely remodelled. It eventually developed into a masterpiece of military engineering with stout walls, carefully planned steps and ramps for moving men and artillery. By the end of the 18th century, more than 400 cannon defended the fort, making it almost impregnable.&lt;/li&gt;&#xd;
&lt;li&gt; San Crist&amp;oacute;bal, with its dependencies, is another accomplished example of the military architecture of the second half of the 18th century.&lt;/li&gt;&#xd;
&lt;li&gt; San Juan National Historic Site includes forts, bastions, powder houses, wall and El Ca&amp;ntilde;uelo Fort, also called San Juan de la Cruz - defensive fortifications that once surrounded the old colonial portion of San Juan, Puerto Rico. El Ca&amp;ntilde;uelo Fort is located at the Isla de Cabras at the western end of the entrance to San Juan Bay.&lt;/li&gt;&#xd;
&lt;/ul&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Between the 15th and 19th centuries, a series of defensive structures was built at this strategic point in the Caribbean Sea to protect the city and the Bay of San Juan. They represent a fine display of European military architecture adapted to harbour sites on the American continent.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>La Fortaleza and San Juan National Historic Site in Puerto Rico</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>296</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(i)(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1984</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/307</http_url>
<id_number>307</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_307.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>40.6894444400</latitude><location>New York, New York</location>
<longitude>-74.0447222200</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The Statue of Liberty is a masterpiece of the human creative spirit. Its construction in the studios of Bartholdi in Paris represents one of the greatest technical exploits of the 19th century. It welcomed immigrants at the entrance to New York harbour, and so it is directly and materially associated with an event of outstanding universal significance: the populating of the United States, the melting pot of disparate peoples in the second half of the 19th century. The fact that the statue, whose funds were raised by international subscription, was executed in Europe, by a French sculptor, strengthens the symbolic interest of this world-renowned work.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;During the second half of the 19th century, the population of the United States almost doubled in 30 years, from 38,500,000 inhabitants in 1870 to 76,000,000 in 1900. This prodigious growth is principally due to immigration which reached an unprecedented high at that time. Between 1840 and 1880, 9,438,000 foreigners landed in the United States, among which, besides the British, were Germans, Irish and Scandinavian. Between 1880 and 1914, the number of immigrants reached 22,000,000, this time deriving mainly from southern and eastern Europe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;It is within this context the order was placed for the Statue of Liberty, made in Paris by the French sculptor Fr&amp;eacute;d&amp;eacute;ric-Auguste Bartholdi, in collaboration with Gustave Eiffel, who conceived and executed the metallic skeleton which was to form the interior framework. The exterior 'envelope' was composed of brass plaques, formed by hammering them in hard wood moulds made from plaster models. These plaques were then soldered and riveted together. After Bartholdi prefabricated the figure in Paris by moulding sheets of copper over a steel framework, it was shipped to the United States in 241 crates in 1885.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the money to erect the statue was contributed by American schoolchildren. It is certain that for millions of immigrants who came to America in the 19th century seeking freedom, it was the fulfilment of their dreams. The sculptor also intended with his work to be an immense and impressive symbol of human liberty, and it is one of the most universal symbols of political freedom and democracy. The people of France gave the statue to the people of the United States over 100 years ago in recognition of the friendship established during the American Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Statue of Liberty, a woman holding on high a book and a 46&amp;nbsp;m long torch set on Liberty Island, situated at the entrance to New York harbour about 1&amp;nbsp;km from the landing point of the immigrants, was dedicated on 28&amp;nbsp;October 1886 and was designated a National Monument on 15&amp;nbsp;October 1924. On 8&amp;nbsp;September 1937, jurisdiction was enlarged to encompass all of Bedloe's Island and in 1956, the island's name was changed to Liberty Island. On 11&amp;nbsp;May 1965, Ellis Island was also transferred to the National Park Service and became part of the Statue of Liberty National Monument.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;'Liberty Enlightening the World' was extensively restored in time for the spectacular centennial of American independence on 4&amp;nbsp;July 1986, for whom it symbolized the ideals of Washington and Lincoln. It has continued to inspire people across the world.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Made in Paris by the French sculptor Bartholdi, in collaboration with Gustave Eiffel (who was responsible for the steel framework), this towering monument to liberty was a gift from France on the centenary of American independence in 1886. Standing at the entrance to New York Harbour, it has welcomed millions of immigrants to the United States ever since.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Statue of Liberty</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>346</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1984</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Act of Congress of 30 June 1864 (13 Stat. 325) granted Yosemite Valley and Mariposa Big Tree Grove to the state of California (regranted to the US government in 1906). Establishment of Yosemite National Park as a forest reservation on 1 October 1890 (26 Stat. 650) excluding Yosemite Valley and Mariposa Grove. Boundary adjustments were made in 1905. Park extension in 1929 of 4,846.47ha and further extensions in 1930, 1931, 1932, 1937, 1938 and 1984. Designated as a World Heritage site in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/308</http_url>
<id_number>308</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_308.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>37.7461111100</latitude><location>California</location>
<longitude>-119.5966667000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Yosemite National Park, on the west slope of the central Sierra Nevada Mountains, is an area of outstanding scenic beauty and great wilderness value. The park represents practically all the different environments found within the Sierra Nevada, including sequoia groves, historic resources, evidence of Indian habitation, and domes, valleys, polished granites and other geological features illustrating the formation of the mountain range.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is dominated by the Sierra Nevada, which is a tilted granite area. Granite underlies most of the park and is exposed as domes, partial domes, knobs and cliffs. There is exceptionally glaciated topography over most of the area including the spectacular Yosemite Valley, a 914&amp;nbsp;m deep cleft carved by glaciers through a gently rolling upland. The valley is a widened portion of the prevailing narrow Merced River canyon which traverses the southern sector of the park from east to west. The massive sheer granite walls present a freshly glaciated appearance with little postglacial erosion. The park is known for its many waterfalls, including the Yosemite Falls and Ribbon Falls, and some 300 lakes, including Emerald and Merced. Other notable canyons in the park are the Grand Canyon of the Tuolumne River and the Tenaya Canyon. There are also two major rivers (Merced and Tuolumne). The area was previously heavily glaciated and, although no glaciers are still existent in the park, the marks of their passing are everywhere. Glacial action combined with the granitic bedrock has resulted in unique and pronounced landform features. These include distinctive polished dome structures as well as the related glacial features of hanging valleys, tarns, moraines and U-shaped valleys. Monolithic granitic blocks such as Half Dome and the perpendicular wall of El Capitan are classic distinctive reflections of the geological history of the area.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The variety of flora is reflected in the existence of six distinct vegetation zones which are governed by altitudinal variation. Notable are three groves of the giant sequoia tree and extensive alpine meadows. There are 1,200 species of flowering plant along with various other ferns, bryophytes and lichens. There is one endemic and eight threatened or endangered species of plant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park has 67 mammalian species, of which 32 are rodents, 221 species of bird, 18 reptile, 10 amphibian and 11 fish, of which 6 are endemic. One bird species (bald eagle) is endangered and the peregrine falcon is listed as vulnerable. A few non-native species have been accidentally introduced such as beaver and white-tailed ptarmigan. Bighorn sheep were declared extinct in Yosemite in 1914 but were reintroduced in 1986.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;There are 1,000 designated archaeological sites recorded by visitors, park staff and during systematic archaeological surveys. Yosemite is viewed as a boundary zone between the two major cultural provinces of Central California and the Great Basin. In late prehistoric and historic times Yosemite was occupied by two main tribes of North American Indians. There are 569 designated archaeological sites within the park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Yosemite's natural beauty was the impetus, then, for the first implementation of the national park concept as we know it today. Adding to Yosemite's cultural importance are the archaeological features found in the area.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Much change has however occurred in the Yosemite landscape. Suppression of natural fires and heavy stock and sheep grazing in the past has also altered the original vegetation.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Yosemite National Park lies in the heart of California. With its 'hanging' valleys, many waterfalls, cirque lakes, polished domes, moraines and U-shaped valleys, it provides an excellent overview of all kinds of granite relief fashioned by glaciation. At 600&amp;ndash;4,000 m, a great variety of flora and fauna can also be found here.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Yosemite National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>347</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1987</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/353</http_url>
<id_number>353</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_353.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>36.0637777800</latitude><location>New Mexico</location>
<longitude>-107.9708333000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Chaco is an example of a prehistoric or protohistoric culture that is remarkable for its monumental public and ceremonial buildings and its distinctive architecture. The cultural sites of Chaco Culture National Historical Park They are part of the history and traditions of the Hopi, the Pueblo peoples of New Mexico, and the Navajo, who continue to respect and honour them. Chaco Canyon is the area with the highest concentration of archaeological sites of the whole zone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;For over 2,000 years, Pueblo peoples occupied a vast region of the south-western United States. In Chaco Canyon, a major centre of the ancestral Pueblo culture between 850 and 1250, many different clans and peoples created a community for ceremonials, trade, administrative and political activity in the prehistoric Four Corners area. In addition to the Chaco Culture National Historical Park, the World Heritage property includes the Aztec Ruins National Monument and several smaller Chaco sites.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Anasazi, sedentary farmers as they were, occupied the greater part of the south-west of what is now the United States. Within this culture the Chacos appear as an autonomous group. This society is characterized by a very elaborate ground occupation system which includes a constellation of towns surrounded by satellite villages and linked by a road network, so characteristic of Chaco culture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The zenith was from around 1020 to 1110. The highly organized reconstruction of old living places, such as Pueblo Bonito and Penasco Blanco, demonstrates their skill in the use of building techniques in a difficult environment. The Chaco people combined pre-planned architectural designs, astronomical alignments, geometry, landscaping and engineering to create an ancient urban centre of spectacular public architecture. Chaco was connected to over 150 communities throughout the region by engineered roads and a shared vision of the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time it illustrates the increasing complexity of the Chaco social structure: circular &lt;em&gt;kivas&lt;/em&gt; having an essentially religious role appeared on a regular basis in the middle of an increasingly differentiated unitary dwelling. More and more roads were built and the signs of extensive trading became more manifest (imports of ceramics and lithic materials, including turquoise). This phase was followed by a period of rapid decadence about 1110. From 1140 to 1200, the Chaco population died out and the pueblos were abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;After 1250, the people migrated from the area, moving south, east and west to join relatives living on the Hopi Mesas, along the Rio Grande, and around Zu&amp;ntilde;i Mountain. The region remained practically uninhabited until the 17th century, when it was taken over by Navajo Indians.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>rev</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;For over 2,000 years, Pueblo peoples occupied a vast region of the south-western United States. Chaco Canyon, a major centre of ancestral Pueblo culture between 850 and 1250, was a focus for ceremonials, trade and political activity for the prehistoric Four Corners area. Chaco is remarkable for its monumental public and ceremonial buildings and its distinctive architecture &amp;ndash; it has an ancient urban ceremonial centre that is unlike anything constructed before or since. In addition to the Chaco Culture National Historical Park, the World Heritage property includes the Aztec Ruins National Monument and several smaller Chaco sites managed by the Bureau of Land Management.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Chaco Culture</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>405</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1987</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Hawaii National Park, created on 1 August 1916 by Act of the US Congress (39 Stat. 432), consisted of two units each on different islands, one on Hawaii Island and the other on Maui Island. The area of the park was more than doubled as a result of Congressional authorisation in 1922 (45 Stat. 503), in 1928 (45 Stat. 424) and in 1938 (52 Stat. 781). The 'Ola'a Forest Tract was donated in 1951 and 1953 (Executive Order #1640). The park was split into Hawaii Volcanoes National Park (on Hawaii Island) and Haleakala National Park (on Maui Island) in 1961 (75 Stat. 577). Hawaii Volcanoes National Park is protected under 16 U.S.C. 1 (National Park Service Organic Act) and under the terms establishing the park as set out in 16 U.S.C. 395b, and under several sections of 16 U.S.C. 391-396a. Hawaii Volcanoes and Haleakala national parks were accepted as MAB Biosphere Reserves in 1980, and combined to form one cluster, Hawaiian Islands Biosphere Reserve, in April 1983. Hawaii Volcanoes National Park is under consideration for inscription on the World Heritage list.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/409</http_url>
<id_number>409</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_409.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>19.4008333300</latitude><location>Hawaii</location>
<longitude>-155.1236111000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Lies in the south-east part of the island of Hawaii (Big Island), the easternmost island of the State of Hawaii, and includes the summit and south-east slope of Mauna Loa and the summit and south-western, southern, and south-eastern slopes of the Kilauea Volcano. The park extends from the southern coast, with its volcanic sea cliff headlands to the summit calderas of Kilauea, the most active volcano in the world (with more than 50 recorded eruptions in the last 33 years up to 1985) and Mauna Loa volcanoes. The latter is a massive, flat-domed shield volcano built by lava flow layers and is considered to be the best example of its type in the world, extending from 5,581&amp;nbsp;m below sea level to 4,169&amp;nbsp;m above.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Hawaii Volcanoes National Park is greatest and the calderas of Kilauea are one of most studied in the world: in fact there is a geologic station dating from 1912.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The climatic gradient varies with altitude from tropical humid to alpine desert.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park contains a high diversity of plant communities with striking life-form and physiognomic differences; 23 distinct vegetation types have been described for the park, ranging from the very diverse tropical rainforest of 'Ola'a to the scrub and grassland of Ka'u and the alpine tundra of Mauna Loa, grouped into five major ecosystems: subalpine, montane seasonal, montane rainforest, submontane seasonal and coastal lowlands. The 'Ola'a Forest tract, over 4,000&amp;nbsp;ha in size, is probably the largest remaining tract of virgin ohia and fern forest in the Hawaiian Islands. The native flora numbering 41 species, with a further 40 listed as rare and warranting special attention.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The park is rich, in archaeological remains particularly along 'the coast with native villages, temples, graves, paved trails, canoe landings, petroglyphs, shelter caves and agricultural areas. Following the arrival of Captain James Cook in 1778-79, Christian influences started in or around 1823, with churches and schools built and the introduction of cattle, goat and &lt;em&gt;pulu&lt;/em&gt; (tree-fern product) harvesting and the encouragement of visitors. Extensive ruins of stone structures dating back to the time of Pa'ao (a high priest) in 1275 are present.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Like all natural areas in Hawaii, the park has been subject to considerable biological alteration since man's arrival. Direct removal or alteration of native forest for growing sugar and pineapple plantations, ranching and logging, has altered the native biota of the forest habitats, particularly at low and middle elevations. Except for a single species of bat Hawaiian hoary bat, native mammalian forms are absent. Little is known to date about invertebrate forms. Avian forms present interesting and significant examples of adaptive radiation and of extinction. Most endemic avian species are rare or endangered. Ranching activities and the introduction of species such as the pig, goat and mongoose have had serious biological consequences, including destruction of native ecosystems and widespread extinction of endemic species. Pockets of standing water, created by the wallowing of the feral pigs, provide breeding places for mosquitoes, resulting in serious avian malaria.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The control programs undertaken on the basis of solid scientific research have been a model for removal of alien animals and plants (including illegal narcotics) on oceanic islands.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;This site contains two of the most active volcanoes in the world, Mauna Loa (4,170 m high) and Kilauea (1,250 m high), both of which tower over the Pacific Ocean. Volcanic eruptions have created a constantly changing landscape, and the lava flows reveal surprising geological formations. Rare birds and endemic species can be found there, as well as forests of giant ferns.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Hawaii Volcanoes National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>472</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(i)(iv)(vi)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1987</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/442</http_url>
<id_number>442</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_442.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>38.0327777800</latitude><location>Virginia</location>
<longitude>-78.5038888900</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Monticello and the University of Virginia are directly and materially associated with the ideals of Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826), better known for his political career, the brilliance of which overshadowed his reputation as a writer and architect. These works of perfection, where the difficult passage from Utopia to reality is harmoniously achieved, are directly inspired by the very same principles which led to Jefferson's Declaration of Independence (1776) and his project for the abolition of slavery (1800).&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of the buildings into the natural landscape, the originality of the plan and design, and the refined proportions and decor make Monticello an outstanding example of a neoclassical work of art, while the University of Virginia is an outstanding example of a great educational institution from the Age of Enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The two major works of Thomas Jefferson in Charlottesville are Monticello and the University of Virginia. Monticello (1769-1809) is a perfect example of a neoclassical &lt;em&gt;villa rustica&lt;/em&gt;, based on a Roman design, revised by Palladio and amended by the Physiocrats. The University of Virginia is a fine example of the architectural ideal of the Age of Enlightenment put to use in the great educational programme of the third President of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Construction of Monticello began in 1769. The very personal conception of the house clearly shows the various influences experienced by its designer: that of Palladio, evidencing in the perfect proportions of the pedimented porticos, and that of the contemporary neoclassical architecture. The interior spatial organization and the low elevation were borrowed from contemporary Parisian town house design. The western facade is dominated by an octagonal dome. Only the harmonious volume of the villa emerges from the foliage of the park where, towards the end of his life, Jefferson planted orchards, vegetable and flower gardens.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Jefferson's most ambitious and last architectural undertaking was the construction of the University of Virginia. Elaborating this project, which is based on educational ideals that are both encyclopaedic and democratic, he departed from pre-existing British or American college planning schemes. The rational layout of this 'academic village' is inspired both by the principles of hygiene laid down by the hospital builders and by a symbolic architecture expressed by the hierarchy of volumes and the repertory of forms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;A half-scale copy of the Pantheon in Rome, which houses the library, dominates the academic village. The 10 pavilions housing the professors of the 10 schools that make up the university are deliberately based on a distinctive design and are intended to serve as an encyclopaedia of classical and neoclassical architectural designs. However, the connecting colonnades serve to give a feeling of unity to this space. The later construction of a building at the south end has unnecessarily transformed this triumphal way into an enclosed space.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Jefferson (1743&amp;ndash;1826), author of the American Declaration of Independence and third president of the United States, was also a talented architect of neoclassical buildings. He designed Monticello (1769&amp;ndash;1809), his plantation home, and his ideal 'academical village' (1817&amp;ndash;26), which is still the heart of the University of Virginia. Jefferson's use of an architectural vocabulary based upon classical antiquity symbolizes both the aspirations of the new American republic as the inheritor of European tradition and the cultural experimentation that could be expected as the country matured.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Monticello and the University of Virginia in Charlottesville</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>513</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iv)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1992</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;The culture of the Pueblo Indians extended through a wide geographical area of northern Mexico and the southwest United States. It can still be found in a certain number of communities in the States of Chihuahua (Mexico) and Arizona and New Mexico (United States). Taos is the best preserved of the pueblos north of the borders defined by the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo (1848).&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Located in the valley of a small tributary of the Rio Grande, Taos comprises a group of habitations and ceremonial centres (6 kivas have been conserved). which are representative of a culture largely derived from the traditions of the prehistoric Anasazi Indian tribes, who settled around the present borders of Arizona, New Mexico, Utah, and Colorado. Their culture went into an irreversible decline, and in the later 13th century major sites like Mesa Verde and Chaco (included on the World Heritage List in 1978 and 1987 respectively) were abandoned, perhaps because of major climatic changes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The proliferation of small pueblos in the valley of the Rio Grande and its tributaries, when considered along with the disappearance of the Anasazi tribes, was one of the major characteristics of the settlement of the North American continent. Modest rural communities. characterized by common social and religious structures, traditional agricultural practices perfected during the &amp;quot;classical&amp;quot; period. and a systematic use of irrigation, were built. Taos is thought to have appeared before 1400.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;In the modern historical period the two major characteristics of the Pueblo civilization were mutually contradictory : unchanging traditions deeply rooted in the culture and an ever-constant ability to absorb other cultures. Their faculty for acculturation gradually began to appear following the first Spanish expedition of the Governor of New Galicia, Francisco Vasquez de Coronado. in 1540-1542. Beginning in 1613, the inhabitants of Taos resisted the system of encomiendas which allowed certain Spaniards to exact a tribute in kind from the village. In 1634 the missionary Fray Alonso de Benavides complained to the Pope of their &amp;quot;rebellious&amp;quot; attitude.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The entire 18th century was a time of wars in which Taos played an important part in resisting the colonizers. However, the breeds of cattle and types of grain introduced by the conquerors were readily adopted into their agricultural system. Attempts to convert the Pueblos to Christianity were ill-received (during the major Pueblo revolt of 1680 the first church was burned down) but unconsciously the religious mentality of the people changed. A similar dichotomy between an irredentist attitude in principle and an assimilation in fact marked the two subsequent historical stages : from 1821 to 1848, under Mexican administration, and from 1848 to the present, under the US administration. In 1970 the people of Taos obtained the restitution of lands usurped by the Government, which included the sacred site of the Blue Lake. At the same time, their ritual ceremonies include both a Christmas procession and the Hispano-Mexican dance of the Matatchines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the village appears at first sight to conform with the description given in 1776 by Fray Francisco Atanasio Dominguez. However, although the earthen enclosure which he likened to one of the Biblical cities survives, numerous modifications can be observed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;To the west, the missionaries' convent and church lie in ruins. A new church was built at a different location of the west side of the north plaza in the 19th century. The multi-tiered adobe dwellings still retain their original form and outline, but details have changed. Doors, which traditionally were mostly used to interconnect rooms, are now common as exterior access to the ground floors and to the roof tops on upper stories. Windows, which traditionally were small and incorporated into walls very sparingly, are now common features. The proliferation of doors and windows through time at Taos reflects the acculturation of European traits and the relaxing of needs for defensive structures. In addition to ovens located outdoors, fireplaces have been built inside the living quarters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/492</http_url>
<id_number>492</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_492.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>36.4388900000</latitude><location>New Mexico</location>
<longitude>-105.5416700000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;Taos is a remarkable example of a traditional type of architectural ensemble from the pre-Hispanic period of the Americas and unique to this region which has successfully retained most of its traditional forms to the present day. Thanks to the determination of the latter-day Native American community, it appears to be successfully resisting the pressures of modern society.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The culture of the Pueblo Indians extended through a wide geographical area of northern Mexico and the south-western United States. Taos is the best preserved of the pueblos north of the borders defined by the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo (1848). Located in the valley of a small tributary of the Rio Grande, Taos comprises a group of habitations and ceremonial centres (six &lt;em&gt;kivas&lt;/em&gt; have been conserved), which are representative of a culture largely derived from the traditions of the prehistoric Anasazi Indian tribes who settled near the present borders of Arizona, New Mexico, Utah and Colorado.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Taos's modest rural community appeared before 1400, characterized by common social and religious structures and traditional agricultural practices. In the modern historical period the two major characteristics of the Pueblo civilization were mutually contradictory: unchanging traditions deeply rooted in the culture and an ever-constant ability to absorb other cultures. Their faculty for acculturation gradually began to appear following the first Spanish expedition of the Governor of New Galicia, Francisco Vasquez de Coronado, in 1540-42.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The entire 18th century was a time of wars in which Taos played an important part in resisting the colonizers. The breeds of cattle and types of grain were introduced by the conquerors into their agricultural system. Attempts to convert the Pueblos to Christianity were ill-received but unconsciously the religious mentality of the people changed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Taos Pueblo shows the traditional method of adobe construction: the pueblo consists of two clusters of houses, each built from sun-dried mud brick, with walls ranging from 70&amp;nbsp;cm thick at the bottom to about 35&amp;nbsp;cm at the top. Each year the walls are still refinished with a new coat of adobe plaster as part of a village ceremony. The rooms are stepped back so that the roofs of the lower units form terraces for those above. The units at ground level and some of those above are entered by doors that originally were quite small and low; access to the upper units is by ladders through holes in the roof. The living quarters are on the top and outside, while the rooms deep within the structure were used grain storage. The roofs are made from cedar logs, their ends protruding through the walls; on the logs are mats of branches on which are laid grasses covered with a thick layer of mud and a finishing coat of adobe plaster. It is a massive system of construction but one well suited to the rigours of the climate.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;In 1970 the people of Taos obtained the restitution of lands usurped by the government, which included the sacred site of the Blue Lake. At the same time, their ritual ceremonies include both a Christmas procession and the Hispano-Mexican dance of the Matatchines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The two main adobe building complexes retain their traditional three-dimensional layout. Certain features, such as doors and windows, have been introduced over the last century. Taos Pueblo represents a natural evolutionary process: it has adjusted to a changed social and economic climate and reflects the acculturation of European traits and the relaxing of needs of defensive structures.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Administration of Taos Pueblo is vested in the Taos tribe, which is deeply conscious of its heritage and of the material expression of that heritage in the buildings of the settlement. The pueblo of Taos has tended to become a seasonal habitat reserved for ceremonial functions and tourist attractions.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension>rev</revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Situated in the valley of a small tributary of the Rio Grande, this adobe settlement &amp;ndash; consisting of dwellings and ceremonial buildings &amp;ndash; represents the culture of the Pueblo Indians of Arizona and New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Taos Pueblo</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>573</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(vii)(viii)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>1995</date_inscribed>
<historical_description></historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/721</http_url>
<id_number>721</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_721.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>32.1666666700</latitude><location>Eddy County, State of New Mexico</location>
<longitude>-104.3833333000</longitude>
<long_description>&lt;p&gt;The park covers a segment of the Permian fossil Capitan Reef.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;An extensive cave system has developed within the reef as a result of sulphuric acid dissolution and of the 81 known caves, Carlsbad Cavern is the largest and Lechuguilla Cave is the most extensive and decorated cave in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The Capitan Reef complex dates back to the Permian period, some 280-225&amp;nbsp;million years ago. The exposed sections of this reef lying within the park are among the best preserved in the world accessible for scientific study. Geologists are able to study the rock formations not only through cave passages which penetrate the reef but also in exposures uncovered through erosion. Fossils include bryozoans, pelecypods, gastropods, echinoderms, brachiopods, fusulinds, sponges, trilobites and algae. Above-ground vegetation communities range from desert to coniferous forest. Some 800 plant species have been identified, of which three are internationally threatened: Sneed pincushion cactus, Lee pincushion cactus and Lloyd's hedgehog cactus. The fauna inventory includes 64 mammals, 331 bird and 44 herpetofauna species.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The caves are noted for their migratory bat species, especially the Mexican free-tailed bat. Various species of fungi and bacteria growing in the caves are of particular scientific and medical interest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Disturbances within the park include permanent damage incurred to speleothems and the cave ecosystem from tourism, decline in bat populations from the use of DDT as well as attempts to eradicate them in Mexico, oil and gas exploration, grazing by trespassing livestock, invasion by exotic fauna and the hunting of puma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Carlsbad is radically different from the other existing World Heritage caves: Carlsbad Caverns National Park is distinguished by its huge chambers which are far larger than similar other as well as for its decorative mineral.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Since its initial exploration in 1985, Lechuguilla Cave has been strictly managed, allowing only closely monitored visits by researchers. This cave is particularly noteworthy as an underground laboratory where geological processes can be studied in a virtually undisturbed environment. The only threat that faces the park is oil and gas exploration near its borders.&lt;/p&gt;</long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;This karst landscape in the state of New Mexico comprises over 80 recognized caves. They are outstanding not only for their size but also for the profusion, diversity and beauty of their mineral formations. Lechuguilla Cave stands out from the others, providing an underground laboratory where geological and biological processes can be studied in a pristine setting.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Carlsbad Caverns National Park</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>852</unique_number>
</row>

<row>
<criteria_txt>(iii)(vi)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria_txt>
<danger></danger>
<date_inscribed>2010</date_inscribed>
<historical_description>&lt;p&gt;Polynesian voyagers arrived in the isolated Hawaiian Archipelago around 300 AD as part of the great migration around the Pacific that started perhaps around 3,000 years ago from south-east Asia, reached Polynesia by around 200 BC, and then spread across the rest of the Pacific over the next two millennia. The voyagers found the larger islands in what is now Hawaii to have fertile soils, abundant water, and reefs rich with marine life.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The settlers mainly inhabited the main islands to the south-east of the Archipelago, but there is evidence of human use in two within Papahanaumokuakea: Mokumanamana and Nihoa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The sites in the two islands have been the subject of only limited archaeological investigation and there are still major gaps in knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;The earliest studies, undertaken by the Tanager Expedition in 1923-24, completely excavated a number of small caves/rock shelters, partly-excavated some open-air sites and removed human skeletal material found in small niches in the cliffs on Nihoa, as well as two human femurs and a tibia revealed by excavation of a rock shelter on Mokumanamana. All the human bone as well as all cultural material retrieved from the excavations and from surface sites were returned to the Bishop Museum in Honolulu. The human skeletal remains have recently been repatriated to the islands by Native Hawaiian cultural practitioners. In addition to completely stripping all sediments observed in cave/rock shelter sites, the Tanager excavations contributed to the destabilization of sections of dry-stone walling on the islands. This and several earlier non-scientific expeditions to the islands also removed a number of small and highly-distinctive carved stone statues and other artefacts from the surface of Mokumanamana. Some of the images are in Bishop Museum but others appear to have been lost.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Recorded human visitation to the two islands has been minimal since the Tanager Expedition, as the islands were part of the Hawaiian Islands Reservation declared in 1909. Access has effectively been limited to shortterm biological surveys, intermittent low-impact archaeological studies and occasional visits by Native Hawaiian cultural practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Two archaeologists, one a Native Hawaiian doctoral candidate and the other the US Fish and Wildlife Service archaeologist responsible for the property, were left on Mokumanamana during the ICOMOS mission to continue the former's PhD project there. It is likely that this research will go a considerable way to filling the remaining major gaps in knowledge of Nihoa and Mokumanamana.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Although little archaeological research has been done elsewhere in Papahanaumokuakea, (the sum total of archaeological work in the whole areas over eighty years apparently only comes to 18 days), the ICOMOS mission confirmed that any obvious signs of pre-European use would have been easily detected by trained professionals. Moreover, palaeoenvironmental investigations conducted on Laysan Atoll by archaeologists amongst other specialists failed to reveal any sign of pre-European human activity in a sediment core dating back some 7,000 years, more than twice as long as people have been anywhere in remote Oceania and more than four times the length of time people are known to have been in the main Hawaiian islands. Polynesian rats (Rattus exulans) were present on Kure until recently but have been exterminated to protect ground-nesting birds whose eggs are highly vulnerable to rat predation. These rats are a commensal species introduced to the remote Pacific by the first human colonists millennia ago and are today carried around on ships along with European rats (although not to the Marine National Monument, as all visiting vessels are subject to strict mandatory rat-control measures). It is not known whether R. exulans was introduced to Kure in the European or pre-European period, but the species is absent from the rest of the Northwest Hawaiian Islands and is not known to have occurred anywhere in Papahanaumokuakea at the time of European contact. However, the absence of commensal rats does not mean early Polynesians did not visit the more remote north-western islands, as there is no evidence they were ever present on Nihoa or Mokumanamana, where pre- European human occupation is undoubted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;When Europeans arrived in Hawaii in the late 18th century they found a thriving society with distinctive and complex social and religious systems. In 1898 Hawaii was acquired by the United States thorough the &amp;lsquo;Newlands Resolution'.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in the 1960s and 70s a resistance movement begin to develop against Western assimilation. This led to a renaissance of Hawaiian culture and the strengthening of bonds with sacred places.&lt;/p&gt;&#xd;
&lt;p&gt;A large body of information on oral history has been published over around a hundred years in local newspapers (e.g., Kaunamano 1862 in Hoku o ka Pakipika; Manu 1899 in Ka Loea Kalai&amp;lsquo;aina; Wise 1924 in Nupepa Kuoko&amp;lsquo;a). More recent ethnological studies (2003) highlight the continuity of Native Hawaiian traditional practices and histories in the North-western Hawaiian Islands. Only a fraction of these have been recorded, and many more exist in the memories and life histories of kupuna.&lt;/p&gt;</historical_description>
<http_url>http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1326</http_url>
<id_number>1326</id_number>
<image_url>http://whc.unesco.org/uploads/sites/site_1326.jpg</image_url>
<iso_code>us</iso_code>
<justification></justification>
<latitude>25.3490700000</latitude><location></location>
<longitude>-170.1458200000</longitude>
<long_description></long_description>
<region>Europe and North America</region>
<revision_extension></revision_extension>
<secondary_dates></secondary_dates>
<short_description>&lt;p&gt;Papahanaumokuakea is a vast and isolated linear cluster of small, low lying islands and atolls, with their surrounding ocean, roughly 250 km to the northwest of the main Hawaiian Archipelago and extending over some 1931 km. The area has deep cosmological and traditional significance for living Native Hawaiian culture, as an ancestral environment, as an embodiment of the Hawaiian concept of kinship between people and the natural world, and as the place where it is believed that life originates and to where the spirits return after death. On two of the islands, Nihoa and Makumanamana, there are archaeological remains relating to pre-European settlement and use. Much of the monument is made up of pelagic and deepwater habitats, with notable features such as seamounts and submerged banks, extensive coral reefs and lagoons. It is one of the largest marine protected areas (MPAs) in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</short_description>
<site>Papahanaumokuakea</site>
<states>United States of America</states>
<transboundary>0</transboundary>
<unique_number>1672</unique_number>
</row>

</query>